<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Logoi Ōraioi. Three seasonable sermons the first preach't at St. Mary's in Cambridge, May 31. 1642. The others designed for publick auditories, but prevented. / By Tho. Stephens, M.A.</title>
            <author>Stephens, Thomas, fl. 1648-1677.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 192 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 69 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A74698</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1839_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R210165</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868989</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868989</idno>
            <idno type="VID">170447</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A74698)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170447)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 229:E1839[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Logoi Ōraioi. Three seasonable sermons the first preach't at St. Mary's in Cambridge, May 31. 1642. The others designed for publick auditories, but prevented. / By Tho. Stephens, M.A.</title>
                  <author>Stephens, Thomas, fl. 1648-1677.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 103 [i.e. 130] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.C. for John Crooke at the ship in St. Pauls Church-Yard.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1660]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Page 130 is misnumbered 103.</note>
                  <note>Date of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aug:".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Judges XXI, 25 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Judges IV, 23 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Numbers XVII, 8 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170447:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ΛΟ'ΓΟΙ 'ΩΡΑ<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>ΙΟΙ.</p>
            <p>THREE SEASONABLE SERMONS The Firſt Preach't at S<hi rend="sup">t.</hi> MARY'S IN Cambridge, <hi>May</hi> 31. 1642.</p>
            <p>The Others deſigned for publick <hi>Auditories,</hi> but prevented.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Tho. Stephens,</hi> M. A.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J.C.</hi> for <hi>John Crooke</hi> at the Ship in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-Yard.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:170447:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170447:2"/>
            <head>A PREFACE to the READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hatſoever <hi>Title</hi> this book carries in the <hi>Front</hi> of it, thou maiſt well cenſure me, for having been <hi>inſtant out of Seaſon,</hi> in obtruding more <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> upon the World; at this time eſpecially, when the <hi>Pulpit</hi> hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt juſtled the <hi>desk</hi> out of the <hi>Church,</hi> and all <hi>Religion</hi> ſeems locked up in the <hi>Preachers</hi> lips: When every <hi>Young Stripling</hi> is ready (with <hi>Ahimaaz</hi>) <hi>to run before he be ſent:</hi> yea, and to <hi>outrun</hi> the <hi>Cuſhi's</hi> too, which have <hi>true tidings</hi> in their mouths; and <hi>knows no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing,</hi> only <hi>tells you of tumults,</hi> ſuch perhaps as he has <hi>raiſed</hi> by the beating of the <hi>pulpit-drum.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>—Et quorum pars magna fult—</q>
            <pb facs="tcp:170447:3"/>
            <p>Such (like the fiſh <hi>Sepia</hi>) caſt their <hi>black infuſions</hi> upon the <hi>wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> in which they Swim, and by <hi>ſtaining</hi> them, do hope not only to <hi>ſecure</hi> themſelves from being taken, but to <hi>poyſon</hi> others too, which delight in <hi>clearer ſtreams.</hi> Miſtake me not in this: I admire, I adore this <hi>Ordinance</hi> of <hi>God</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> this <hi>power of God unto ſalvation:</hi> But it is then only, when it is <hi>Gods ordinance:</hi> when it doth not reſiſt another <hi>ordinance of God:</hi> when the <hi>throne</hi> is not pul'd down to make room for the <hi>Doctors chair;</hi> and the <hi>word of God</hi> made a <hi>vizor</hi> to cover the deformities of <hi>Sathans Miniſters.</hi> VVhen <hi>Corah</hi> and his <hi>confederates</hi> (notwithſtanding their <hi>pretended Holyneſſe</hi>) ſhall contend with <hi>Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron</hi> for a <hi>ſhare</hi> in <hi>holy Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions;</hi> true <hi>Iſraelites</hi> will ſeparate <hi>from their Congregations.</hi> Neither can I admire <hi>Saul</hi> (any <hi>mad frantick
<pb facs="tcp:170447:3"/>Enthuſiaſt</hi>) although <hi>among the Prophets.</hi> The condition of that <hi>patient</hi> is very deplorable, to whom <hi>poyſon</hi> is adminiſtred by an unskil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>emperick,</hi> inſtead of <hi>Cordialls</hi> and <hi>Reſtoratives;</hi> and the ſtate of that people is no leſs deſperate, when a <hi>lying Spirit</hi> in the <hi>Mouthes</hi> of the pretended <hi>Prophets,</hi> ſhall perſwade them to <hi>go up to fight to their own deſtruction.</hi> Tis true that <hi>Faith cometh by hearing.</hi> But it is by hearing the word of <hi>God,</hi> not <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented</hi> upon by the <hi>Devill:</hi> for as <hi>preaching</hi> at firſt begat <hi>faith,</hi> in our dayes it has uſher'd in <hi>hereſies, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneſſe, Libertiniſm,</hi> I had all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt ſaid <hi>Infidelity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>ſnuffing</hi> of theſe new <hi>lights</hi> is the deſign of theſe following ſheets: VVhich were intended for the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick long ago; even then when theſe <hi>Calves</hi> of <hi>Bethel</hi> bleated loudeſt: and ſo they may ſecure the Author
<pb facs="tcp:170447:4"/>from the ſiniſter end of <hi>time ſerving.</hi> But alas <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> may remember the dayes (and oh that we could not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member them) when the <hi>mouth of the Ox was muſled:</hi> even that <hi>Ox</hi> that <hi>trod out the corn,</hi> might nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>low</hi> nor <hi>eat:</hi> Never did <hi>Nation</hi> run more in parallel to <hi>Iſrael, 2</hi> Chron. <hi>15.3.</hi> which <hi>for a long time had been without a true God, and without a teaching Prieſt, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Law.</hi> Tis true, <hi>Gods cauſe</hi> was cryed up, but <hi>Gods Vicegerent</hi> puld down; <hi>teachers</hi> we had many, but <hi>teaching prieſts</hi> but a few, <hi>Sauls footmen had turned againſt them, becauſe their hands had been with David.</hi> And a <hi>Law</hi> we had still, <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runtamen incluſum in tabulis, tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam gladium in vagina reconditum</hi> A law <hi>claps'd</hi> up in our <hi>Bibles;</hi> but pul'd down in our <hi>Churches:</hi> when the bear reading of the <hi>ten Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements</hi> (the fifth eſpecially)
<pb facs="tcp:170447:4"/>was cauſe enough of a ſequestration.</p>
            <p>But bleſſed be God, who out of mercy to his Church (then viſibly ruined) did ſtill preſerve a <hi>remnant in Iſrael,</hi> many <hi>thouſands that never bowed their knee to Baal;</hi> though ſome of them were <hi>hid in caves and fed by ſtealth:</hi> bleſſed be God that ſuffered not our <hi>lamp</hi> to be quite ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſht, although it burnt in the <hi>Socket,</hi> but kept it <hi>light,</hi> till there was freſh <hi>Oyl</hi> and better times to <hi>trim</hi> it in. Bleſſed be God that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the eyes of our <hi>Elyes be wax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en dim,</hi> yet before the <hi>lamp of God be quite gone out in the Temple of the Lord,</hi> they have time ſtill to call ſome <hi>Samuels</hi> to the <hi>miniſtration: An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient</hi> men [I know) that have ſeen the <hi>firſt houſe</hi> (as in <hi>Ezra's</hi> dayes) may <hi>weep with a loud voice,</hi> to find our Church go leſs, leſs both in power at home and <hi>reputation</hi> abroad; yet that noiſe of weeping may be drown'd
<pb facs="tcp:170447:5"/>with <hi>ſhouting aloud for joy, that God has left us a remnant to eſcape, and given us a nail in his holy place, and lightned our eyes, and given us a reviving in our bondage.</hi> Ezra <hi>9.8.</hi> So that although <hi>Jachin</hi> our <hi>eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment</hi> be ſhaken, yet <hi>Boaz</hi> our <hi>ſtrength</hi> ſtands upon its <hi>baſis</hi> ſtill.</p>
            <p>'Tis fabled of the old <hi>Arcadians</hi> (who fancied themſelves to be born before the moon) that,</p>
            <q>—Occiduum longe Titana ſecuti Deſperare diem—</q>
            <p>—They followed the ſetting <hi>Sun</hi> to their utmoſt borders, and there they bad good <hi>Night</hi> to light, deſpairing of a <hi>ſecond day.</hi> But we need no <hi>Poeticall illuſtrations</hi> to ſet a <hi>gloſſe</hi> upon our true <hi>fears;</hi> Many a bleed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing heart and weeping eye attended upon <hi>Englands</hi> funeral when our <hi>Sun</hi> was ſet, and we could expect no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but an eternal night of <hi>horror</hi> and <hi>confuſion;</hi> when the bloody
<pb facs="tcp:170447:5"/>and barbarous <hi>Regicides,</hi> could not believe the King was <hi>ſure</hi> enough, till they had <hi>murdered</hi> the <hi>Kingdom</hi> too, and in the place of it had foiſted in a <hi>miſhapen monſter</hi> called by them a <hi>Common-wealth:</hi> but an <hi>al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty power</hi> hath called <hi>light</hi> out of <hi>darkneſſe;</hi> he hath ſaid to <hi>dead bones, live,</hi> and whereas in other <hi>acts</hi> of <hi>providence</hi> we may ſee his finger, here <hi>with his own right hand and holy arme he hath gotten himſelf the victory.</hi> Far be it from me, to rake in the <hi>Aſhes</hi> where the coals of <hi>diviſion</hi> lye <hi>buried up,</hi> and for want of <hi>Air</hi> will ſoon be <hi>extinguiſht;</hi> the <hi>wound</hi> is <hi>cloſed,</hi> and I hope ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly <hi>cured</hi> that it will never <hi>feſter</hi> at the <hi>bottom</hi> to need a ſecond <hi>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pening. Chriſts coat</hi> was <hi>ſeamleſs;</hi> I dare not <hi>rend</hi> it. <hi>Tros Tyriusve</hi>— True <hi>Trojan</hi> or falſe. <hi>Carthaginian</hi> ſhall never more be termes of diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence: And ſince his <hi>Sacred Majeſty</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:170447:6"/>in his most <hi>Gratious Declaration</hi> has <hi>deſired</hi> and <hi>ordained</hi> that <hi>hence for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward all Notes of diſcord ſeparation and difference of parties be utterly aboliſhed,</hi> I will not be ſo unchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> or ſo diſloyall a <hi>ſubject</hi> to diſobey ſuch just <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands.</hi> Eſpecially remembring the <hi>Propheticall</hi> judgment of that <hi>bleſt Saint and glorious Martyr King CHARLES I. That none will be more loyal &amp; faithful to his Majeſty, then thoſe Subjects who ſenſible of their errors and his injuries will feel in their own ſouls moſt vehement mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives to repentance, and earneſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires to make ſome reparations for their former defects.</hi> Thoſe hands which have been deepeſt dyed in blood if they prove eminent <hi>ſupporters</hi> of the <hi>throne</hi> will be waſht from their former guilt:</p>
            <q>
               <l>Scire piget poſt tale decus quid fecerat ante,</l>
               <l>Hanc vidi, ſatis eſt hanc mihi noſſe manum.</l>
            </q>
            <pb facs="tcp:170447:6"/>
            <p>Now that God, that <hi>baptized us all into one body whether Jews or gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, whether bond or free,</hi> unite all <hi>intereſts</hi> into the grand <hi>concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of <hi>peace</hi> and <hi>righteouſneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having therefore this <hi>charity</hi> for others I cannot have a diſtruſt of theirs to me, by a <hi>ſuſpicion</hi> that this <hi>Paraeneſis</hi> to <hi>Loyalty</hi> will ſeem un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſonable to any, although it was prepared for the most <hi>diſloyal</hi> times: For the first of theſe <hi>Sermons</hi> was preacht in the <hi>Univerſity</hi> immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after his Majeſty of bleſſed memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry had retired into the <hi>North</hi> to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void the rude and unſeemly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portment of the tumultuous rabbl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſo to eſcape the <hi>raging of the waters and the madneſs of the People:</hi> Where the acceptance which it found aroſe not from any intrinſick worth it had (I dare not flater my ſelf with ſo vain a conceit) but from the <hi>ſui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tableneſſe</hi> of the <hi>ſubject</hi> to the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of that learned and religious
<pb facs="tcp:170447:7"/>
               <hi>Auditory;</hi> For the good <hi>King</hi> hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing lately paſſed that way, had left ſo deep an <hi>impreſſion</hi> upon the <hi>hearts</hi> of the <hi>Loyal Students</hi> that any man was welcome to them who was <hi>a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moria</hi> (his ſhall I ſay? Or) their <hi>Remembrancer of him:</hi> And here it had dyed with that <hi>Generation that ſoon after paſſed away,</hi> had it not come to the knowledg of ſome of our <hi>Countrey-Committee-men,</hi> four years after (ſome men have long <hi>ears</hi>) for whom I have reaſon to bleſs <hi>God,</hi> who raiſed them up as inſtruments to make me <hi>be thought worthy to ſuffer any thing for that righteous cauſe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Doctor</hi> Holdſworth,</note> Yet the <hi>Reverend</hi> and <hi>pious Vice-chancellor</hi> obliged me then to another <hi>courſe;</hi> to ſupply which, the Second <hi>Sermon</hi> was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared, (upon a <hi>Text</hi> which had been <hi>blaſphemed</hi> in that <hi>Pulpit</hi> not long before) which happened ſoon af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the <hi>Signall battail</hi> of <hi>Edghill.</hi> But
<pb facs="tcp:170447:7"/>alas! when I came to <hi>ſuck</hi> the <hi>breaſts</hi> of my <hi>dear Mother</hi> I found them <hi>rub'd</hi> over with <hi>gall</hi> and <hi>wormwood;</hi> The <hi>Scene</hi> was chang'd <hi>Athens</hi> was turned to a <hi>Mars's hill.</hi> The <hi>Muſick</hi> of <hi>Apollos harp</hi> could not he heard for the noiſe of <hi>trumpets:</hi> For on the night before, that MAN OF BLOOD came down with a <hi>troop</hi> of <hi>horſe,</hi> which was then his only com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand (the <hi>Cockatrice</hi> at that time was but an <hi>egg</hi>) and had blockt up the <hi>Pulpit</hi> with his <hi>Janizaries;</hi> ſo that <hi>prudence</hi> bad me retire, unleſſe I would <hi>mingle my blood with my ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third <hi>Sermon</hi> was compoſed for a <hi>Viſitation,</hi> at what Time I (the unworthieſt of thoſe that wait upon <hi>Gods Altars</hi>) by the favour of a <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Prelate,</hi> was <hi>nominated</hi> to an <hi>Eccleſiaſtical dignity.</hi> But thoſe <hi>places</hi> fell in the day of <hi>Gods Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation,</hi> and the <hi>Sermon</hi> proved <hi>abor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:170447:8"/>If any thing contained in them may conduce to the ſettlement of <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State,</hi> or <hi>inflame</hi> thee to a conſcionable diſcharge of thy duty in reference to both, I have my end. Give <hi>God</hi> the <hi>glory;</hi> and let him have the benefit of thy <hi>prayers</hi> who is,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine in all Chriſtian Offices <hi>T. Stephens.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Bury St. Edm.</hi>
                  <date>
                     <hi>June 6. 1660.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:170447:8"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Judges 21. 25.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>In thoſe dayes there was no King in Iſrael; every man did that which was right in their own eyes.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hen <hi>thoſe dayes</hi> have been, and they have been in <hi>Iſrael</hi> too; we have <hi>Scripture</hi> for it, ſayes our <hi>Phanatick,</hi> and why may they not be again? This place I confeſs is plain enough, and as well urged on this occaſion, as his, who maintained his <hi>heterodox</hi> opinions from St. <hi>Pauls</hi> poſition, Cor. 1.11. <hi>Of neceſſity hereſies muſt be amongſt you</hi>—But wo be to that man by whom theſe things come to paſs. When <hi>Every man</hi> muſt be his own Carver, and ſits Judge upon his own actions, there is no <hi>King</hi> indeed, but whole legions of <hi>Tyrants;</hi> each domineering affection, every luſting thought, all Baſtard-off-ſprings, the <hi>unreaſonable</hi> appetites of our <hi>reaſonable</hi> ſouls, will Lord it over us: Take away this <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> muſt needs follow: <hi>Kings</hi> we may have ſtill, but no <hi>Subjects</hi> to obey; <hi>every man</hi> will be his own Ruler, yet every man as unruly as he was before.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:170447:9"/>
            <p>Where there is ſo much confuſion in the text, you can expert no curious method in the proſecution of it. An <hi>Anarchy</hi> and the <hi>effects</hi> of it do divide it. <hi>Iſrael had no King,</hi> there is the <hi>Fountain:</hi> but the <hi>rivulets</hi> ſtream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from it, they are divers: there is <hi>diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> enough in the effects: as many parts as men, <hi>every man</hi> has his ſhare, they are all in <hi>action,</hi> and actions ſpeciouſly <hi>good</hi> too, they are <hi>every man doing right,</hi> if themſelves may be both judge and parties. Their eyes are the <hi>Lesbian</hi> rules which meaſure the works of their hands: <hi>Phyſiologers</hi> tell us a crooked object is received into the eye by ſtrait beams: <hi>Crooked</hi> things may ſeem <hi>ſtrait;</hi> that may be <hi>right</hi> in our eyes, which is <hi>wrong</hi> in Gods eyes, that notwithſtanding <hi>we walk in the wayes of our own heart, and in the ſight of our own eyes,</hi> Eccl. 9. 9. <hi>Yet for all theſe things God will bring us into Judgment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My Text will bear no long Doctrinall diſcourſe, neither know I whether I may more properly call it a <hi>history</hi> of thoſe times or a <hi>propheſie</hi> of theſe: for I am ſure (<hi>muta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to nomine</hi>) we are as deeply concerned in it, as the <hi>Jews</hi> themſelves. I ſhall briefly, but more plainly acquaint you with the <hi>ſtory,</hi> then in the <hi>Analogy</hi> make application to our ſelves.</p>
            <p>When the pleaſure of God had called
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:170447:9"/>the People of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> to be his own peculi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar inheritance, he did not preſently and at the firſt, eſtabliſh one perpetuall form of <hi>Government,</hi> or ſet the <hi>imperial</hi> Crown upon the head of his <hi>Anointed,</hi> but uſhers in the <hi>Royalty</hi> of a <hi>King</hi> (which <hi>Abraham</hi> enjoyed long before in a <hi>Prototype</hi> by way of promiſe, Gen. 17.) with ſome inferiour ſubordinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>power:</hi> from <hi>Captains</hi> he gave them <hi>Judges,</hi> next to them his <hi>Prophets,</hi> then <hi>Judges</hi> back again: as if Almighty God contrived a way, how beſt, and upon the beſt experience, he might be a ſafeguard to his own people. But when theſe <hi>undertitles</hi> could not prevail againſt the daring outrages and bold preſumptions of the tribes, he then exalts his <hi>throne,</hi> creates his <hi>Viceroy;</hi> the old <hi>Scoene</hi> diſappears, and he diſcovers his <hi>King upon his holy hill of Sion.</hi> And here he ſtops; no change from hence: St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> proves it for this cauſe the beſt becauſe it was the laſt, no <hi>ſuperſedeas,</hi> no removal from it. Thus as the <hi>Epigrammatiſt</hi> congra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulates diſeaſes and honours them with the title of the firſt inventors of <hi>Phyſick,</hi> we may bleſs the ſores of the Common wealth which did produce ſo <hi>Soveraign</hi> a ſalve, or rather bleſs <hi>God</hi> which did prepare an <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dote</hi> for, yet out of ſuch abominable Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanies.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:170447:10"/>
            <p>For in this <hi>interregnum</hi> of <hi>judiciary</hi> power, when <hi>the ſins of the people had devoured their Judges</hi> (as the Prophet ſpeaks, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 7.7.) when Owle-ey'd iniquity durſt ſee the Sun (<hi>Da Phaebe veniam ſi quid illicitum tui videre vultus!</hi>) and the high hand of ſin diſdained the coercive power of their <hi>petty</hi> Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates; God raiſes up a new ſucceſſion of <hi>Princes,</hi> a race of <hi>Kings,</hi> which might ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs ſuch inſolencies. Which were ſo notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in this <hi>evening</hi> of the <hi>Judges,</hi> when their authority was now a ſetting, that the holy Spirit records three ſtories unparalleld by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny place of Scripture. And leſt the cauſe of all might be miſtaken, four times in theſe four Chapters, the ſame words are again repeated, <hi>In thoſe dayes, when thoſe were acted, there was no King in Iſrael:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt <hi>Micah</hi>) from a converted <hi>theife</hi> turns a ſuperſtitious <hi>innovator.</hi> He made an <hi>Idol</hi> of the Silver before, or elſe he would never have ſtolne it; but now emptying his ſoul of one Divel, he gives another free entertainment. Should our true ſervice of <hi>God</hi> Almighty be half ſo dear, <hi>I</hi> fear his Temples would not be ſo well cuſtomed. But what he got lightly, he ſpends as liberally: Out go the eleven hundred Shekells, <hi>quantum nummorum ſervat in arca, tantum habet &amp; fidei;</hi> his <hi>religion</hi> was as high prized as his <hi>mony</hi> could purchaſe;
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:170447:10"/>
               <hi>Gods houſe</hi> was not enough for him, he muſt have an <hi>houſe of Gods,</hi> an <hi>Ephod</hi> and a <hi>Tera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phim,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> pretty new found <hi>Dieties,</hi> which muſt preſerve their maker, give a <hi>well-being</hi> to him who but juſt now gave them their <hi>being.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Old Woman</hi> his mother (a ſex well skilled in ſuch new-fangled religions) ſhe likes very well of this new ſtamp'd devotion, and gives a <hi>bleſſing</hi> to him who brought a <hi>curſe</hi> upon her and all her family.</p>
            <p>But what ſhall we do for a <hi>Prieſt</hi> to offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciate to his golden vanity. Oh! <hi>Micah's</hi> very good at creating: His <hi>reverence</hi> cannot onely <hi>conſecrate</hi> a God but <hi>ordain</hi> his Miniſter too: <hi>Holy orders</hi> are very cheap, where <hi>religion</hi> it ſelf is at a loſs; A <hi>God</hi> of <hi>gold</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not eaſily want ſervants, there will be ſome <hi>Chryſes,</hi> ſome <hi>Calchis</hi> left. Rather then fail his Son ſhall be <hi>conſecrated;</hi> the Hebrew word (if you look in your margins to the 5th. verſe of the 17. Chap, of this b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ok) is (<hi>he filled the hand of his Son</hi>) ingagement enough to this following <hi>ſervice;</hi> once <hi>fill the hand</hi> and you have <hi>heart</hi> and all: We would not care ſo much for <hi>conſecration,</hi> if the <hi>golden breaſtplate</hi> did not accompany it.</p>
            <p>Yet leaſt his new born piety may want ſome ſpecious pretence, a poor Journey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man <hi>Levite</hi> is heard of, ſuch one as God
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:170447:11"/>curſes. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.36. That <hi>he ſhall come and crowch and ſay, put me into the Priests office that I may eat a morſell of bread:</hi> Such a <hi>Titi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>villitius</hi> I ſay upon high way of acquaintance ſhall be content for 10. Shekells of Silver, a ſuit of cloaths and victuals beſides, to cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to ſerve this <hi>Idol</hi>-God: thus is our <hi>Familiſt</hi> confirmed in his new moulded Frame of <hi>devotion,</hi> his <hi>independent</hi> congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and all this while, <hi>there was no King in Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Next come your <hi>Danites,</hi> and there is a <hi>Tribe,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, there is danger in a multitude, they have <hi>hands</hi> as well to practiſe as <hi>heads</hi> to plot their miſchiefs: A <hi>private thiefe</hi> may abound with ſpoiles, but when a <hi>whole army</hi> turnes pillagers that Country muſt needs be deſolate. Well! what fair mask did their vice borrow to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver this inſolence? Their <hi>Country</hi> forſooth was too little for them, their <hi>climate</hi> was too cold. Five Brethren muſt be ſent out for ſpies to diſcover the fatneſs of the land, that they might come and taſt of the <hi>cup which flowed with milk and honey:</hi> Theſe as they paſs by <hi>Micah's</hi> houſe, hear the <hi>Levites</hi> voice which ſojourned there; ſure he had good <hi>lungs,</hi> that his <hi>tongue</hi> could ſo eaſily take acquaintance with the high-way travellers: Ten pound a year will be ſoon talked out, if
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:170447:11"/>he ſpeak ſo loud: but hearing him, they muſt needs hear ſomething from him; An <hi>exhortation</hi> from him will crown the work which they are in hand with: an act of blood if the pulpit bleſs it, muſt needs carry the <hi>Lord</hi> with it? He bids them <hi>go in peace,</hi> incouragement enough for them to prepare for <hi>waar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laiſh</hi> is their next ſtage, a quiet, careleſs, ſecure people, <hi>qui damna nec metuunt nec pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant,</hi> as free from fearing danger as intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it. With theſe glad tidings they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn and <hi>inrich the Danites</hi> ears: They now moſt truely make up <hi>Jacobs</hi> their Fathers propheſie <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.17. they turne <hi>Serpents by the way and Adders in the path. Albertus</hi> tells us, the Nature of the Creature is to fly from a <hi>cloathed</hi> man, but to ſet upon him if they find him <hi>naked:</hi> The <hi>Maacathites</hi> and <hi>Geſhurites</hi> which live amongſt them, are <hi>ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med</hi> men, let them alone 'tis dangerous med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with them; but ſecure <hi>Laiſh</hi> had nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſtrength nor men to aid it, the <hi>Zidoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> were at a farr diſtance, ſix hundred fighting men well appointed might do good ſervice there: <hi>The land is very good, why ſit you ſtill, ariſe, make haſt, enter and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But <hi>Micahs</hi> houſe affoorded them ſo good entertainment in their firſt journal, hat
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:170447:12"/>they'l not balk it now in their ſecond pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs. We have found <hi>idolatry</hi> upon Mount <hi>Ephraim,</hi> ſay the ſpies; an <hi>Ephod</hi> and a <hi>Teraphim,</hi> a <hi>graven Image</hi> and a <hi>molten Image,</hi> fine golden <hi>Idols,</hi> all of <hi>Micah's</hi> making, let us invite them on this journey with us: And there is a <hi>Levite</hi> too, no doubt but <hi>he</hi> will be content, to follow his <hi>golden Gods,</hi> and then aſſuredly we ſhall <hi>go and proſper.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Well! however they loved their <hi>Idolls</hi> well, (or elſe they would never have built <hi>high places</hi> to them afterward) ſure I am they loved the <hi>gold</hi> better: <hi>Micah's</hi> houſe is rifled, his <hi>Oratory</hi> ſpoil'd; his <hi>guardian Gods</hi> could not now defend themſelves: <hi>Sacriledge</hi> and <hi>Burglary</hi> are met together; and that falſe hireling <hi>Levite</hi> whom he took for his <hi>Prieſt,</hi> and <hi>Father</hi> proves his <hi>betrayer.</hi> He ſtands to make good the paſſage amongſt the <hi>armed</hi> men in the gate, <hi>En filii tunicam:</hi> his lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen <hi>Ephod</hi> is turned into a coat of <hi>Male,</hi> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, his place he changed, but not his <hi>office:</hi> He thought it ſafer offending with a multitude; a <hi>Tribe</hi> in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> or two facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Towns of that one Tribe, <hi>Zorah,</hi> &amp; <hi>Eſhta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ol,</hi> may well ſecure an <hi>Idoll Prieſt</hi> who goes triumphing in the midſt of the Cutthroats.</p>
            <p>If his Mr. <hi>Micah</hi> come crying after for reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, he may be anſwered in the <hi>wolves</hi> lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage to the <hi>Crane,</hi> who plucked the ſheeps<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bone
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:170447:12"/>out of his throat. Away thou fool thank me thou haſt thy head, which I might have ſo eaſily ſnapped off when I had thy long bill in my mouth: Speak ſoftly <hi>Micah,</hi> theſe are <hi>angry fellows,</hi> and if thou talk much of thy <hi>Gods,</hi> thou maiſt looſe thy <hi>Life,</hi> and all: Our next work is to plunder <hi>Laiſh</hi> to put all the <hi>inhabitants</hi> to the ſword, and fire the City. And all this while, <hi>there was no King in Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, that no ſociety, neither of <hi>Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, Tribes,</hi> or <hi>Cities</hi> might be cleer, whilſt the <hi>Danites</hi> are bathing themſelves in inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent blood, the Citizens of <hi>Gibeah</hi> are acting a wickedneſs, farr more horrid, much more barbarous: A poor <hi>Levite</hi> of Mount <hi>Ephraim,</hi> whom love and charity had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled to his offending <hi>Concubine,</hi> takes a weary journey after her to <hi>Bethlem Juda,</hi> and overtaking her he was ſo far from put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting her to the ſhame which the publick Law requir'd againſt adultery, that he makes honourable proviſion for her more eaſie and ſpeedy return; there is a couple of Aſſes with bread, and wine, and provender, him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and a ſervant to attender her. After ſome complementall interchanges of cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſie with his <hi>Father-in-law,</hi> he begins his journey homeward: Whilſt the <hi>Sun</hi> ſhaming to behold the barbarous act of the <hi>Gibeonites</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:170447:13"/>ſets upon him: Well, <hi>Gibeah</hi> he enters, when the courteſie of the inhabitants affoorded him the <hi>high way</hi> for his lodging place, where the <hi>Earth</hi> might be his bed, and the <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens</hi> his Canopie; for what ſhould a <hi>Man of God</hi> do in a houſe of one of theſe <hi>Sons of Belial?</hi> And this is the portion of honeſt <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites.</hi> The young <hi>Fellow</hi> in the laſt ſtory that mouth'd it ſo well that his voice might be known at diſtance, found better entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at <hi>Micah's</hi> hand. Once ſell your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience and you may ſoon buy Reſpect. You need not be a <hi>Prieſt</hi> to <hi>Idols</hi> as he was: the <hi>People</hi> will make an <hi>Idoll</hi> of you, fall down and worſhip you.</p>
            <p>It happens that a poor old <hi>labouring</hi> man, a ſojourner there among them, a ſtranger, it ſeems, to them, but more to their incivility, as he returned home from the field, ſpied theſe new <hi>gueſts</hi> of their city: He hails to them friendly, invites them to his homely cottage, and courteouſly imbraces them: When after proviſion of ſuch ſimple delicates, as his not curious palate had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided for himſelf, they chear themſelves in the freeſt expreſſions of loving ſouls. But their mirth is ſoon blaſted: The noyſe of violence is a <hi>Voyder</hi> to the Feaſt. The houſe is beſet by <hi>Incubuſſes,</hi> thoſe <hi>hot Devils</hi> will not be <hi>cooled</hi> unleſs the <hi>Stranger</hi> be given out
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:170447:13"/>to ſatiate their luſts. We may wonder no longer why they were no freer to entertain him in their <hi>houſes,</hi> ſince we finde by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that they <hi>expoſed</hi> him in the ſtreets, that they might the more eaſily <hi>expoſe</hi> him to their injuries.</p>
            <p>Well, to avoid this <hi>nefandum,</hi> this unheard of wickedneſs, a leſs miſchief is imbraced: his <hi>Concubine</hi> is offered up as a <hi>Sacrifice</hi> to thoſe <hi>Divels;</hi> whom they <hi>raviſh,</hi> nay <hi>raviſh her to death;</hi> Theſe were the acts which were ſo good in their own eyes: <hi>Idolatry</hi> in Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, <hi>Burglary</hi> in Counties, <hi>Rapes</hi> in Cities, and all theſe becauſe there <hi>was no King in Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And good reaſon for it. For firſt a <hi>King</hi> amongſt them <hi>would,</hi> Secondly none but a <hi>King, could</hi> curbe ſuch licentious practiſes; he <hi>would</hi> I ſay, for he is the <hi>Miniſter of God which beareth not the ſword in vain. Rom.</hi> 13. He is <hi>Gods</hi> avenger and <hi>executes his wrath on evill doers;</hi> It is the cowardly nature of ſin that it flies away from the <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> though it be gathered into a Troop, like a heard of deer from a bearded Lion: Like the <hi>Lace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daemonian</hi> Servants, who durſt not adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture themſelves, after they had made a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious head, into their Maſters preſence, although they came armed with nothing but ſwitches in their hands: and this, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:170447:14"/>their <hi>inward guilt</hi> affright them, or Gods <hi>mark</hi> on his <hi>Anointed</hi> charme them to obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience. 'Twas quivering <hi>Oreſtas</hi> reply in <hi>Euripides</hi> (before his fault was publiſhed) to that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; what feavour ſhakes thee? 'oh 'twas <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; 'twas a cold fit of conſcience which would end in a burning fit of hell. And I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded that it was ſomething more then our Saviour <hi>Chriſts</hi> Divinity which amazed that band Soldiers with their curſed <hi>Captain Judas,</hi> when they came to take him <hi>John</hi> 18. that they <hi>went backward and fell to the ground:</hi> Something more I ſay: For ſhould he have called his <hi>Divine</hi> Power to aſſiſt him, he might have commanded ten thouſand of <hi>Legions</hi> of <hi>Angels</hi> to have reſcued him; nor would he the ſecond time ſo freely have of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered himſelf into their hands.</p>
            <p>Then for the other, God hath beſtowed upon all <hi>Magistrates</hi> an eſpeciall Character, to ſecure them from any dangerous conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racies: <hi>Touch not mine annointed,</hi> (ſay's <hi>David,</hi>) <hi>Chro.</hi> 1.16. my <hi>Meſſias</hi> ſaith the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginal; as if the brow of <hi>Majesty</hi> were the neareſt draught, the livelieſt repreſentation of <hi>Almighty God:</hi> from hence they were ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured in the pureſt times by the beſt <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians</hi> with ſuch appellations as did befit their greatneſs; their words, <hi>divalis juſſio</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:170447:14"/>the audible voice of God, their preſence, <hi>ſacraveſtigia,</hi> the cleareſt footſteps of the Diety.</p>
            <p>But then ſecondly, no other <hi>Eſtate</hi> or or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>could,</hi> at leaſt <hi>could ſo well</hi> ſuppreſs ſuch daring impieties; <hi>de facto</hi> we find they did not, not that they wanted an eſtabliſht form of <hi>Government,</hi> for we cannot believe that God would leave <hi>his People</hi> deſtitute: An <hi>interregnum</hi> of <hi>Judges</hi> here we find, from <hi>Sampſons</hi> death to <hi>Samuel:</hi> But <hi>High-Prieſts</hi> ſtill contiuned. Yet what power had they, when <hi>Corahs</hi> infection (like <hi>Pliny's</hi> ſeeds kept many ages in the ground before they ſprout,) began now to <hi>grow</hi> again, and every <hi>Micah</hi> durſt diſpence his <hi>holy Orders,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrate a <hi>Prieſt</hi> of his own, good enough for a <hi>Religion</hi> of his own inventing? And for their <hi>Judges</hi> (had they at that time in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy'd them) whether <hi>Evill Succeſs</hi> under them, or <hi>Cruel Oppreſſion</hi> by them, had ſo ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enated the peoples mindes, that in the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry next generation, <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.8. finding <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel ſons turning aſide after lucre,</hi> and <hi>taking bribes,</hi> and <hi>perverting judgment,</hi> they with one mouth cry out for a <hi>King,</hi> for a <hi>King</hi> in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> which might appoint <hi>every</hi> man to do that which is <hi>right,</hi> not in <hi>their own eyes,</hi> but in the <hi>eyes of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us now make <hi>Iſrael</hi> our looking glaſs,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:170447:15"/>and compare both our <hi>Eſtates</hi> and <hi>Actions</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, that thus laying theſe two <hi>crooked</hi> lines together, we may between them draw a <hi>right</hi> one, a <hi>right</hi> one, not as we our ſelves, but as our <hi>Overſeers,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, thoſe which watch over us, ſhall determine.</p>
            <p>Firſt where have we any <hi>City,</hi> nay any <hi>Street,</hi> nay almoſt any <hi>Family,</hi> where <hi>Micah</hi> and his <hi>Mother,</hi> private Spirits, have not ſet up their <hi>Idols,</hi> their new ſtamped divinity? which <hi>Proteus</hi>-like changes ſhapes ſo oft, that two dayes old 'tis grown out of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg: <hi>Error</hi> I have heard ere now compared to <hi>Hydra</hi> that monſter with a hundred heads, but ſtill the crown of <hi>truth</hi> was conſtancy: the Eldeſt <hi>Daughter</hi> of Almighty God, and ſo took place from her <hi>Fathers</hi> titles, and ſhe was alwaies one and the ſame: But ſure in theſe dayes ſhe hath either degenerated into <hi>error</hi> or borrowed ſo much of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of it, as that ſhee's as various as the minds of thoſe which are the aſſertors of her: and as <hi>Micahs</hi> Idols are here raiſed out of that ſtock which he firſt ſtole from his <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> coffers, the <hi>mint</hi> of our Religions moſt commonly are ſome <hi>old wifes traditions,</hi> which <hi>new molten</hi> and new moulded work ſo deep an impreſſion in our credulous ſouls, that they juſtle out the moſt ſolemn, devout, eſſentiall, divine parts of our <hi>ſervice</hi> of God:
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:170447:15"/>Blaſphemous wretches! (<hi>I</hi> tremble to ſpeak what theſe ears have heard) who durſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe our <hi>Saviour</hi> of indiſcretion, and his <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles</hi> of preſumption, for leaving two ſuch Legacies, a <hi>Prayer</hi> and a <hi>Creed</hi> to the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding <hi>Church:</hi> Nay the very <hi>Canon</hi> of holy <hi>Scripture</hi> muſt wait for approbation in their corner Synodals, or elſe be no longer <hi>Canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call:</hi> Bleſt <hi>Saviour!</hi> thou didſt once extort a Confeſſion together with the blood of the Apoſtate <hi>Julian</hi> that his wounds open'd their mouthes with a <hi>Viciſti Gallilaee,</hi> now <hi>Chriſt</hi> thou haſt the upper hand: <hi>Ariſe O God, plead thine Own cauſe, remember how the fooliſh man reproacheth thee dayly: forget not the voice of thine enemies, the preſumption of them that hate thee increaſeth ever more and more.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For <hi>Micahs</hi> diſpencing holy <hi>Orders</hi> to his Son, alas we can ſpare that Labour, there is a rank ſmell of <hi>Popery</hi> breath'd out of the very name of <hi>Orders: Orders</hi> do ſuppoſe <hi>distinctions.</hi> We can be every man his own <hi>Prieſt:</hi> witneſs our <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> the new ſprung ſect of <hi>Sebaptiſts</hi> and our other <hi>Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts;</hi> we can <hi>pray</hi> for our ſelves, <hi>inſtruct</hi> our ſelves, <hi>Baptize</hi> our ſelves, <hi>bleſs</hi> our ſelves, <hi>curſe</hi> our ſelves, and what you will: <hi>Dii ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem terris avertite pestem!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet perhaps if ſome young <hi>Levite</hi> with a luſty voice will take ten ſhekels and a
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:170447:16"/>ſuit of Cloaths, he may be put into imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. <hi>Pudeat dicere Academici! ex nobis no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtra eſt perditio;</hi> the <hi>Vipers</hi> which have eaten through the bowels of the <hi>Church</hi> are our own off-ſprings: Theſe creep into the <hi>Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit,</hi> God knows from whence, as ſome cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary birds at the time of the year into hollow trees, where out of <hi>zealous ignorance</hi> they dare declaim againſt all <hi>Authority</hi> as <hi>Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian,</hi> all <hi>antiquity</hi> as <hi>heretical,</hi> all <hi>moral-learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> as in it ſelf <hi>damnable,</hi> which I confeſs is the beſt plea for their own ignorance.</p>
            <p>The old <hi>Egyptians</hi> in their <hi>Hieroglyphical</hi> Characters made the <hi>Hyaena</hi> a <hi>Symbol</hi> of <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie,</hi> which beaſt (if we believe <hi>Ariſtotle</hi>) had the power to blinde the <hi>Shepheards</hi> and make the Dogs dumb, then counterfeiting the <hi>Paſtors</hi> voice, the ſimple <hi>Sheep</hi> came at their call and ſo were devoured by them: whether <hi>Natures</hi> Store-houſe have furniſhed the World with ſuch a traiterous brood of creatures I will not here determine. But I am ſure <hi>Religion</hi> has found too many of them. They creep into Congregations and <hi>blind</hi> the eyes of the Lawful <hi>Paſtors,</hi> and perhaps have inſinuated ſo farr into the hearts of the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly that they make him dumb too, he may not be heard to ſpeak: his <hi>Bells</hi> are <hi>crackt,</hi> his <hi>Pomegranates</hi> have <hi>loſt their Savour:</hi> Theſe are the only Spokesmen, and that ſo
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:170447:16"/>lowd, that the ſpies that travell by, may hear them, but the poor <hi>ſheep,</hi> which dance attendance to their deceitfull voice, eſcape well if they loſe nothing but their <hi>fleeces:</hi> Our Saviour <hi>Christ</hi> in 23 <hi>Math.</hi> 14. gives us intimation of ſuch as <hi>upon a pretence of long prayers devour Widdows houſes; I</hi> doubt, the woe comes down to theſe times: I'me ſure the <hi>Levite</hi> here with <hi>Micahs</hi> Religion had packed away <hi>Micahs</hi> Eſtate too, if we look narrower to it: for thats the poor Mans complaint in the 24. Verſe of the 18. Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that <hi>he had no more left;</hi> and how many ſad ſtories teach us when <hi>Souls</hi> and <hi>bodies,</hi> Goods and Goodneſs, Eſtates, and Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, have been ſhipwrack'd altogether. Well: <hi>Micahs</hi> ſtory thats made up and in all this <hi>we have done that which it right in our own eyes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Next come the <hi>Danites;</hi> where <hi>I</hi> ſhall not apply the <hi>circumstances,</hi> there is too much envy would wait upon them: But I am ſure we have <hi>Zorahs</hi> and <hi>Eſhtaols</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, factious <hi>Towns</hi> and <hi>Cities,</hi> which can furniſh us with a tumultuous brood of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contented <hi>Brethren,</hi> which think their bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders are too ſtraight, they muſt let out their appetites, and make more room for their active ſouls. And if <hi>Micah</hi> have a ſolitary houſe upon mount <hi>Ephraim</hi> in the way, let
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:170447:17"/>him take heed of pillaging: the ſuſpition of an <hi>Idol</hi> within his doors, will be enough co confiſcate all his goods and gold too, to this <hi>Exchequer;</hi> And truly if their Inſolen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy be not curbed, I beleeve they will diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver many unknown <hi>Idolaters:</hi> Scarce a <hi>Gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmiths</hi> ſhop ſhall be paſt by, but ſome graven <hi>Image</hi> ſhall be found in it to make it a lawful booty.</p>
            <p>But if the ſeverity of the <hi>Law</hi> do reſtrain ſuch private <hi>Burglaries,</hi> yet <hi>Gods</hi> houſe is ſure to go to it. There be <hi>Idols</hi> in the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: that's watch-word enough for a riotous <hi>Aſſembly:</hi> force open the <hi>Doors,</hi> break down the <hi>Windows,</hi> let the <hi>ſpies</hi> enter and the <hi>armed men</hi> keep the paſſage: but once in, tis not the <hi>Altar and Rails</hi> will ſerve them, no the <hi>Veſtry</hi> &amp; the <hi>Library,</hi> yes the <hi>poor mans box</hi> ſhall be ſuſpected to have a golden <hi>Image</hi> in it: Nay there is no place ſecure, there is an <hi>Idoll</hi> in the <hi>Desk:</hi> away with the book of <hi>Common-prayer,</hi> teare it to pieces: There is an <hi>Idoll</hi> in the <hi>Pulpit</hi> too, or rather the <hi>Prieſt</hi> of <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolls;</hi> hale him, pull him out, tear off the ſacred Veſtments from his ſuperſtitious ſhoulders: The <hi>Ephod</hi> and the <hi>Teraphim</hi> will not ſuffice; the <hi>Surplice</hi> and the <hi>Hood: Cherubims</hi> and <hi>Seraphins</hi> muſt all away, nay the very ſtones of the pavement ſhall be torne up, becauſe men kneel upon them;
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:170447:17"/>Thus, <hi>O God, do they break down the carved works of thy houſe with axes and Hammars.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Prophet <hi>David</hi> in that <hi>Pſalm</hi> of <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentations</hi> (where he drops as many <hi>tears</hi> from his eyes as <hi>letters</hi> from his pen, for the Deſolation of the <hi>Sanctuary</hi>) Pſal. 94. complains of the havock thoſe unruly bands had made in the midſt of the Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: And the <hi>Septuagint</hi> Copies, (whether upon a Miſtake in the firſt tranſcribing, or of ſet purpoſe <hi>I</hi> know not) render that word, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> by <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of burning his <hi>Synagogue,</hi> they ſay they will forbid his <hi>Feſtivals:</hi> And ſure between thoſe two there is a moſt near relation. No readier gap laid open for the neglect of Gods <hi>Sabbaths,</hi> then the prophanations of his <hi>Holy Temples:</hi> If the <hi>Beauty</hi> of holineſſe once be loſt, there will be very few that will continue <hi>Saitors</hi> to it: Set a cheap price upon Religion, and it will find but few Cuſtomers.</p>
            <p>Yet who ſhall be the Ring-leader to this furious rout, but the young <hi>Levite</hi> who had covenanted to be <hi>Micah's</hi> ſervant? His voice at firſt call'd in the Spies to ſearch the houſe, and now is the joyfulleſt man to be in the midſt of the Aſſembly. How many curſed <hi>Chams</hi> hath our Church found, <hi>quae tanquam ſorex ſuo periit indicio,</hi> ſuch who are the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dieſt to diſcover their <hi>Parents</hi> nakedneſs;
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:170447:18"/>ſuch who being <hi>Hirelings</hi> and not true <hi>Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards,</hi> as our Saviour calls them, <hi>John</hi> 10. enter not by the door, but climbe in ſome other way, <hi>the ſame are thieves and robbers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor yet will this <hi>Levite</hi> forſake his <hi>Golden Gods,</hi> he hoped I believe, ere long to have ſome limb or other of his <hi>Idoll</hi> ſtamp'd into leſſer pieces and gingle in his pocket. His Mr. <hi>Micah</hi> was but a private man, and ten ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kells but a poor reward for the hazarding of his Soul: but if a <hi>Tribe</hi> of <hi>Iſrael</hi> will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain him, chooſe their Religion hee'l be their Miniſter, hee'l ſerve them in it. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though we for ought find, when they were ſettled where they would be, they caſheer'd him &amp; <hi>Jonathan</hi> was conſecrated in his ſtead: 'Tis ſo with us; <hi>Religion</hi> is a good cloak though many times <hi>Covetouſneſs</hi> and <hi>Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg</hi> are hid under it. <hi>Dionyſius</hi> pluckes off <hi>Aeſculapius</hi> his golden beard in <hi>Apollo's</hi> Temple, not out of fear of <hi>Idolatry</hi> leaſt the people ſhould fall down and worſhip it, but that he alone might adore it, when it was locked up ſafe in his own Coffers: Thus all the holineſs of ſome of our Reformers has ere now proved but <hi>ſacra fames auri:</hi> a reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious itch their fingers have had to be telling the Gold of the <hi>Sanctuary,</hi> which hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly proved an <hi>Achans</hi> wedge, corrupted and conſumed the heap to which 'twas laid.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:170447:18"/>
            <p>Thus the <hi>Danites</hi> ſtory that's made up too, and in all this we have <hi>done that which is right in our own eyes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Laſt is the rape in <hi>Gibeah:</hi> but in ſins of that nature we ſcorne to have patterns ſet us; wee'l out do all examples; that which once was ſaid of <hi>Rome,</hi> is now more true of <hi>England, illic impune peccare licet:</hi> we dare ſin without controul; elſe what mean thoſe ſcandalous, adulterous, inceſtuous copu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, acted as if it were in deſpight <hi>(quam ingenioſa eſt haec nequitia)</hi> under the noſe of thoſe Courts which formerly have puniſhed them?</p>
            <p>But cloſer yet, this <hi>Ephraimite</hi> was a <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vite</hi> which travailed thus patiently after his offending <hi>Concubines;</hi> but returning among the <hi>Benjamites,</hi> he finds them ſo far eſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged from civil hoſpitality, that <hi>pro diſco dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num,</hi> luſt back'd with violence is their moſt friendly ſalutations: None here I hope will deny but the <hi>Miniſters</hi> in the <hi>Goſpell</hi> are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpouſed to their ſeverall Congregations: God Almighty is the <hi>Father</hi> which gives them in this myſticall <hi>Marriage.</hi> Where after much pains and patience, long ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and meekneſs they have travailed to reclaim their errors, and call them back to their firſt Loves: if they paſs by the <hi>Benja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites</hi> (<hi>thoſe ravenous wolves which love to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:170447:19"/>the prey, and devide the ſpoyl, Gen.</hi> 49.27.) 'tis well if they finde high-way re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, and not be cudgeld out of that too. The <hi>Lyons</hi> courteſie goes a great way now, (<hi>I</hi> aſſure you,) when he did no injury: More likely the young Children of the <hi>Bethlemites</hi> will meet them in the ſtreets and cry <hi>go up thou bald head, go up thou bald head;</hi> but for their <hi>Concubines</hi> the benefices, every man muſt be better acquainted with them: They will lie with them, that is, <hi>Know them,</hi> one after another, make their ſeverall <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriation</hi> of them, and that all night, ſo long till they have made a cuſtome of it: So that in the morning when this poor <hi>Concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bine</hi> returnes to her Lord the <hi>Levite,</hi> ſhe ſhall neither have life or heat to comfort him.</p>
            <p>If a poor old Sojourner, one that hath e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to do to ſecure his own head from vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence amongſt them, ſhall take theſe tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veilers under his roof to protect them from the fury of the Citizens, he runs the ſame danger with them, and well if the proſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of his own <hi>Daughter</hi> can quit him from their hands: Gods mercy to his <hi>Church</hi> is ſuch, that he hath alwaies raiſed up ſome to vindicate the reputation of it: yet ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times they are ſo far overborne that good <hi>Obediah,</hi> that Patron of the Prophets is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:170447:19"/>hour in danger of his own deſtruction 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 18. And whotſoever ſhall be ſo religious as to undertake their Patronage, although he plead not for <hi>Bigamy,</hi> plurality of Concubines (the old <hi>Ephraimite</hi> here did not ſo) but only that they may quietly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy the freedom of the place with what the Law of God and nature gives them, yet this very plea may indanger the proſtitution of his own <hi>Daughter,</hi> the publication of his own <hi>Eſtate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus the <hi>Gibeonites</hi> ſtory, that's made up too, and in all this we have done that <hi>which is right in our own eyes:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You ſee the effects are come home to us within our doors, but the <hi>cauſe</hi> you will tell me fails: For in <hi>theſe dayes</hi> we have a <hi>King</hi> in this our <hi>Iſrael:</hi> And God be bleſſed that in theſe dayes we have a <hi>King:</hi> may the dayes of this <hi>King,</hi> in himſelf and his Royall race indure for ever: Yet let me tell you there is no great difference between having no <hi>King,</hi> and a <hi>King</hi> no whit obey'd: Or if any be, the latter is the moſt extreme, if <hi>malum culpae</hi> exceed that of <hi>poenae;</hi> for ſo we alter it from a puniſhment of God to a ſin of our own.</p>
            <p>When every churliſh <hi>Nabal</hi> ſhall refuſe to let diſtreſſed <hi>David</hi> enter commons with his own day-labourers, and partake of ſuch
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:170447:20"/>proviſion as he had made for his <hi>ſheep-ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers,</hi> denying the leaſt portion of his Eſtate, to <hi>Davids</hi> uſe, when the ſecurity of all his Eſtate conſiſt, in <hi>Davids</hi> protection: And if <hi>Ahimelech</hi> the <hi>Priest</hi> (which has ſcarce bread enough to put in his own belly) ſhall feed him with ſome few loaves of the <hi>Sanctuary,</hi> and ſo refreſh and ſtrengthen him with a little Conſecrated bread (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though in the mean time he faſt himſelf for it) it ſhall be cauſe enough for ſome treacherous <hi>Doeg</hi> to inform againſt him; and the next news will be <hi>Sauls</hi> command to his foot men, <hi>his Militia,</hi> to turne and ſlay the <hi>Prieſts</hi> of the Lord, becauſe their hands are with <hi>David.</hi> When every re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viling <hi>Shimei</hi> as he paſſes by the high-way may freely and without controul curſe the <hi>Lords Anointed;</hi> Nay more throw <hi>ſtones</hi> and <hi>durt</hi> upon him; beſpatter <hi>his</hi> unble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſht name, and poyſon <hi>his</hi> reputation with malitious and falſe ſlandours, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcourſes, of moſt dangerous Conſequences: When <hi>Achitophel</hi> his own boſome Friend and choiceſt Counſellour ſhall provoke all <hi>Iſrael</hi> againſt him, and put down <hi>Joab</hi> the Captain of the <hi>Kings</hi> Hoſt, and ſet ſet up <hi>Amaſa</hi> in <hi>his</hi> room: When <hi>Sheba</hi> the <hi>Benjamite</hi> [neither Prieſt nor Prophet] ſhall dare to blow the Trumpet in the high
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:170447:20"/>way, renounce <hi>David</hi> and ſend <hi>every man of Iſrael to their tents:</hi> When the King and all <hi>his</hi> Servants ſhall be forced from <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> that Royall City, and receive no en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment as he paſſes by <hi>Bahurim,</hi> till he come to <hi>Mahanaim</hi> far off, where old <hi>Barzillay</hi> remembers his Duty, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forms <hi>his allegiance</hi> better. If theſe ſcattered drops do fore-token a black ſtorm a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; if theſe <hi>thick miſts</hi> which fall ſo faſt, may eaſily convince us that our <hi>Suns</hi> a ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, we need not go farr to ſeek a cauſe for thoſe forenamed <hi>Inſolencies.</hi> I am ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, <hi>Sirs,</hi> when I behold the pureſt times of our <hi>Religious Forefathers,</hi> and ſee thoſe bleſſed <hi>Martyrs,</hi> even when they were dreſſed up in <hi>flames,</hi> and accompanied <hi>Eliah</hi> to heaven in a <hi>charret</hi> of <hi>fire,</hi> when they were grinding between the teeth of Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, when they were driven to the tops of Mountains like ſo many ſheep to the ſlaughter; when their ingenuous Tortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers were overcome at their own art, and could invent no puniſhment anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to their patience: Then, at their hower of ſuffering, to hear them pray for their <hi>Perſecutors,</hi> to hear them poure out their <hi>Souls</hi> in their moſt pious devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, for a bleſſing on the heads of thoſe <hi>Tyrants</hi> under whom they ſuffered: fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:170447:21"/>againſt them indeed, but <hi>cum precibus &amp; lachrimis,</hi> with thoſe melting ſwords of <hi>prayers</hi> and <hi>tears:</hi> And we, which injoy all thoſe bleſſings which a peacable government can inrich a Land with, we which <hi>fit every man under our own Vines, and our own figtrees</hi> partaking of the fatneſſe of the Land; vve vvhich are vvith as much ſeverity kept off from <hi>idolatry,</hi> as the Old <hi>Christians were</hi> inforced to it, vve vvhich novv hear the bells toll quietly to bring us together to the publick <hi>ſervice</hi> of God, which (were it not for this government) we might expect would be jangling in a more diſmall tune, ringing a funeral peal to the Town or City; that we <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> We <hi>Proteſtants</hi> ſhould <hi>conceive</hi> a miſchief againſt the King in our private bed-cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers; nay more, ſhould unbridle our tongues ſo farr as to <hi>expreſſe</hi> thoſe <hi>thoughts,</hi> nay more yet; ſhould put thoſe thoughts and words in Action, and <hi>lift up the finger</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Lords Annointed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I bring not in a <hi>Ziſca's</hi> drum, a ratteling of the elements to terrifie Children with fantaſtick fears; I would to God the times were ſuch that I might give my ſelf the lie. But alas ye all know 'tis true; it is, and hath been acted: We have a minde to <hi>Micahs</hi> Idols, to <hi>Dan's</hi> robbery, to <hi>Gibeas</hi> rape, and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:170447:21"/>therefore we are for no King to Iſrael.</p>
            <p>The confuſion of my Text is ſo great, that I have loſt all Method, <hi>I</hi> will not ſeek now to recover it: but ſhut up all with one <hi>Paraeneſis.</hi> You ſee the <hi>evil,</hi> 'tis general, it extends to <hi>every man:</hi> and there is but one <hi>Salve</hi> too, which we can properly call, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a <hi>King</hi> amongſt us: A pretious oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment 'tis, and as pretiouſly to be laid up, laid up by <hi>prayers</hi> for him, by <hi>hands</hi> with him, by <hi>purſes</hi> to him of all good ſubjects. The breath of our noſtrils, the life of our liberties, the ſtrength of our hopes the pillar of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion: his Commiſſion is ſigned from Heaven, <hi>Pro.</hi> 8.15. <hi>By me Kings raign.</hi> His Authority is conferred by Heaven, Chron. 1.16. <hi>He is the Anointed of the Lord:</hi> His power deſcends from Heaven, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 21.1. <hi>The King ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce in thy ſtrength, O Lord:</hi> Obedience to him is required from Heaven, 1 Pet. 2. <hi>It is the will of God that you ſubmit your ſelves to the government of your Kings.</hi> I have heard the Prophet <hi>David</hi> ſuſpected by ſome as partial in his own cauſe; juſt like the <hi>Northern Borderers,</hi> who conceived the eighth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment <hi>(Thou ſhalt not ſteal)</hi> to be none of Gods making, but foiſted in by <hi>Henry</hi> the Eight, to ſhackle their theeviſh fingers: I am ſorry that ever the Truth of <hi>Scripture</hi> ſhould depend upon the <hi>arbitrary</hi> opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:170447:22"/>of <hi>men:</hi> but if <hi>S. Paul</hi> have gained a better credit with them, I dare oppoſe the 13. Chapter of his Epiſtle to the <hi>Romans,</hi> againſt the power of <hi>Men</hi> or <hi>Devils</hi> which would trample upon the neck of <hi>Kings: Let every ſoul he ſubiect;</hi> mark the ſtile: There's a <hi>Statute Law</hi> enacted in the high <hi>Parliament</hi> of Heaven, which no man that owns a ſoul may break without high <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> againſt man, and higher <hi>impiety</hi> againſt God. But if our doughty valour have got ſo much confidence as to fight againſt the <hi>Spirit of God,</hi> the apprehenſion of our own advantage might be a powerful argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, me thinks, to eſtabliſh this doctrine: Since in vindicating the right of <hi>Princes</hi> we aſſert <hi>our own:</hi> By ſetting up a <hi>King</hi> in <hi>If<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> we pull down <hi>Micah's</hi> Idols, we ſtop the <hi>Danites</hi> forces, we quell the luſt of <hi>Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beah.</hi> 'Tis <hi>Our</hi> battels he fights, 'tis <hi>our</hi> Laws he enacts, 'tis <hi>Our</hi> Liberties he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fends, 'tis our Life he protects: <hi>he</hi> watches for us, <hi>he</hi> is expoſed to perſonal hazards for us, <hi>he</hi> writes for us, <hi>he</hi> draws the Sword for us.</p>
            <p>Ye know the old ſtory of all the <hi>mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers</hi> mutenying againſt the lazy <hi>Belly:</hi> The accuſation was, that it conſumed all, but got nothing: but they denying their uſual contribution, you'l ſoon finde who went to
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:170447:22"/>the worſt of it. The <hi>hands</hi> were, feeble, the <hi>mouth</hi> pale, the <hi>feet</hi> weak, and the <hi>whole Common-wealth of the body</hi> was out of frame. If <hi>Moſes</hi> do not ſtand in the top of the <hi>Mount,</hi> with the Rod of God in his hand, Exod. 17. and hold up his hand too; <hi>Ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lek</hi> will ſoon overcome the camp of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God hath bleſt this Land to the Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of our Neighbours round about, with a <hi>Prince</hi> in whom <hi>Righteouſneſs and Peace have kiſſed each other,</hi> and carſed for ever be the <hi>bramdles</hi> of <hi>Jotham,</hi> which would overſhadow the <hi>Cedars</hi> of our <hi>Libanon:</hi> But were he as deteſtable for his vices as he is now honourable for his vertues, this were no fair plea for our diſobedience: A wicked King may be an effect of Gods <hi>wrath</hi> againſt a Nation; but the removal, the taking away this wicked <hi>King,</hi> that's hotter, that's <hi>plain fury,</hi> Hoſ. 13. 11. Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe him very <hi>wicked,</hi> he ha's the more need of thy prayers to make him <hi>better.</hi> Suppoſe him to be a <hi>Tyrant,</hi> he will give the fairer occaſions to exerciſe thy vertue of <hi>Patience.</hi> Suppoſe him to be a <hi>Perſecutor,</hi> hee'l do thee a courteſie, he will ſend thee to <hi>Heaven</hi> by violence. It is not <hi>oleum gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae,</hi> but <hi>Dominii,</hi> that Kings are anointed with: <hi>Saul</hi> was touched with this <hi>Oyl</hi> long
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:170447:23"/>before the <hi>Spirit</hi> of God came upon him, and this <hi>Oyl</hi> was not wiped off, it ſwam uppermoſt ſtill, it had the preheminence long after, when that <hi>evil ſpirit</hi> did poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe him.</p>
            <p>If we took to the ſtory of the 26 of the firſt Book of <hi>Samuel,</hi> when <hi>Sauls</hi> guilty con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience gave him leave to ſleep in the trenches of <hi>Hachilah,</hi> with his men of war round about him, we ſhall finde as many arguments to arm <hi>Davids</hi> hand againſt him, as ever met to depoſe a <hi>Soveraign</hi> Title: Firſt on <hi>Sauls</hi> part, he was an unnatural <hi>Tyrant</hi> againſt his own ſon <hi>Jonathan,</hi> he was a bloody <hi>Perſecutor</hi> of the <hi>Prieſts</hi> of God; he was a ſacrilegious <hi>Uſuper</hi> of their holy <hi>Offices,</hi> he was a <hi>deamoniacal</hi> furious man poſſeſſed with a <hi>Devil:</hi> Next on <hi>Davids</hi> part, his <hi>life</hi> was ſought for, and by ſparing <hi>Saul</hi> he ſhould undo himſelf: he had all the opportunity that <hi>night</hi> and <hi>ſecurity</hi> could ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter to him: he was <hi>Sauls</hi> adopted ſon by <hi>Michals</hi> marriage, he was <hi>ſucceſſour</hi> to the Kingdom by the <hi>Prophets</hi> unction; and yet for all this, as if he had been a Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion to maintain the right of <hi>Princes,</hi> he ſtops <hi>Abiſha</hi> with a <hi>quis unqum? Who can lift up the hand againſt the Lords anoynted?</hi> And he that did it afterward, though upon <hi>Sauls</hi> own intreaty (if himſelf may be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:170447:23"/>found him as ſtout a revenger, as he was a bold challenger: He brings News of <hi>Sauls</hi> Death, but is ſent after him the grave. I am amazed, Sirs, when I hear mention of the <hi>Loyalty</hi> of ſome old <hi>Heathen,</hi> ſome of them expoſing their bodies to the deadly ſtroak of the enemies, to ſecure the perſon of their <hi>Emperors.</hi> Others leaping alive into their Funeral piles, as if they could do them no later, no greater ſervice. But I will name no more, leſt their duſt fly in our eyes, ſo blinde and eclipſe the glory of <hi>Christians:</hi> For let me ſeriouſly put the queſtion: Are we <hi>Chriſtions?</hi> Do we know the vertue of in <hi>Oath?</hi> What think we then of that ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn <hi>Oath</hi> of our <hi>Allegiance?</hi> An <hi>Oath</hi> which can receive no <hi>diſpenſation,</hi> no <hi>abſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> from what power ſoever: Are we <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants?</hi> Nay one ſtep farther yet; are we <hi>Proteſtors?</hi> What think we then of that branch of the late <hi>Protestation, that I will maintain the eſtabliſht doctrine of the Church, as it ſtands in oppoſition to Popery and Popiſh Innovations:</hi> I conceive this mainly material to the work in hand, therefore give me leave a while to inſiſt upon it.</p>
            <p>What is the doctrine of the School of <hi>Jeſuits, Bellarmines</hi> poſition will fully tell us, <hi>non licere Chriſtianis tolerare regem haereticum,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:170447:24"/>&amp;c.</hi> Princes falling into <hi>Apoſtacie</hi> from the faith or <hi>hereſie</hi> in the faith, loſe all dominion over their Subjects: and our own Countriman, <hi>Parſons</hi> goes a little farther, that the <hi>People</hi> if they can gather ſtrength ſufficient ought to depoſe ſuch an unworthy <hi>Governour:</hi> and like apt Scholars they will learn their leſſon quickly; for thus a <hi>Jacobine</hi> with an Aſſaſſination ſhall ſoon make good in pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe what their School hath taught them. Thus without much ſtraining they make good the Text: Thoſe there work their pleaſure becauſe <hi>there was no King in Iſrael,</hi> theſe here will have no <hi>King</hi> becauſe they might the more freely work their pleaſure.</p>
            <p>Contrary to this is eſtabliſhed doctrine of the Church of <hi>England</hi> in the 37th. Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle: <hi>The Kings Majeſty his the chief power in this Realm of England, and his other Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions: and is not, nor ought to be ſubject to any Juriſdiction whatſoever, but may and muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strain with the ſword the Stubborne and Evil do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers:</hi> Farr different (it ſeemſ) from that he is tobe reſtrained by Stubborne and Evil-do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, upon a pretence of <hi>his evill doing:</hi> To which purpoſe are thoſe ſix parts of the <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily</hi> againſt <hi>Rebellion</hi> ſo full and appoſite that we muſt either diſclaim them from being the interpreters of the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of our <hi>Church,</hi> or ſit down convinc'd in the manifeſt truth of this aſſertion.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:170447:24"/>
            <p>To theſe I ſhall and the Teſtimony of ſome unqueſtioned <hi>Divines</hi> amongſt us, purpoſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly avoiding the authority of ſuch who are amongſt ſome men (perhaps, unworthily) ſuſpected, leſt their names prove a blemiſh to the <hi>Calendar:</hi> Biſhop <hi>Cranmer</hi> (in his <hi>Neceſſary Erudition for Chriſtian Men</hi>) (A work compoſed by him and other Divines of <hi>Henry</hi> the Eight, and printed long ſince by the ſame <hi>King</hi>) upon the fifth Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, declares that, <hi>by it we are bound not to withdraw our Fealty Truths Love and Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence from our Princes, for what cauſe ſoever it be, nor yet for any cauſe may we conſpire againſt his Perſon, nor do any thing towards the hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drance or hurt thereof or of his, Eſtate.</hi> Not long after, <hi>Biſhop Hooper,</hi> upon the ſame com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement determines, that if <hi>he be naught, that rules the place he is in, it is the Order and work of God: ſo if thou put a difference between the Office it ſelf which is good, and the Officer which is evill, it ſhall keep thee in a religious fear that thou reverence a good and godly Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment in a bad Governour. Biſhop Latimer</hi> a Companion of them both (in a <hi>Sermon</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Twelfday</hi>) tells us, that <hi>we may for nothing in the World</hi> (obſerve the Univerſality) <hi>rebell against the Ordinance of God, that is the Magistrate.</hi> All theſe three glorious <hi>Saints</hi> did in their Actions conſirme their Doctrine,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:170447:25"/>and in the days of Queen <hi>Mary</hi> received the triumphant crown of <hi>Martyrdom,</hi> obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her in ſuffering for that, which their conſciences would not give them leave actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to perform. Next them comes that painfull and Reverend Biſhop <hi>Jewel,</hi> who diſpuring the Caſe with <hi>Harding</hi> drawes iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue in the ſtory <hi>Chilperick</hi> of <hi>France:</hi> whom the <hi>Nobles</hi> depoſed; the <hi>people</hi> were conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with it, and then Pope confirmed it, (rebellion as well ſtrengthened as we could wiſh) yet did his Succceſſor <hi>Pepin</hi> ſcarce ever with quiet injoy the Kingdom; and of the nine Generations (which were all that of that race ſucceeeded) hardly one was found which went down into the grave in peace. Dr. <hi>Humpheryes</hi> Sermons upon <hi>Abiſha</hi>'s ſtory 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 26. are ſo full to our cauſe in hand, that I ſhould do him wrong to cite any part of him, and not ſpin it put to a juſt Treatiſe: <hi>I</hi> referr yee to the book it ſelf; as alſo to Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop <hi>Bancrofts Engliſh-Scottzing;</hi> Biſhop <hi>King</hi> in his 35. Lecture on <hi>Jonas</hi> makes it the very caſe of the <hi>Browniſt,</hi> who in his refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation would tread Conſcience, Obedience, Religion and Duty both to God and Man under foot. Whereupon the Reverend Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop <hi>Davenant</hi> in his twelfth determined Queſtion tells us, <hi>induant quam venlint pietatis larvan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> isti Magiſtratuum</hi> (marke that <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtratuum</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:170447:25"/>not <hi>Religionum</hi>) <hi>reformatores, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biniani tamen Nigriani out Caſſiani rectius au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient, quam Chriſtiani;</hi> Let them mask un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der what cloak they will, <hi>Religion</hi> may be their plea, but <hi>Rebellion</hi> is their practiſe. <hi>I</hi> ſhall forbear the envy of naming ſuch as are ſtill alive amongſt us, of whom Biſhop <hi>Morton</hi> is not the leaſt; But one paſſage of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend <hi>Primate</hi> of <hi>Armagh</hi> in a ſpeech in the <hi>Caſtle Chamber</hi> may not be forborne, becauſe of the Univerſality of the poſition: <hi>There is nothing ſo contrary to the nature of Soveraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> (which <hi>I</hi> hope we ſtill allow our <hi>Kings,</hi> if not how fell they from it?) <hi>as to have any Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour power to over-rule them: Qui Rex eſt, Regem (Maxime) non habeat: I</hi> forbear <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ravia,</hi> becauſe although one of our <hi>Church,</hi> yet a ſtranger born; and the Learned <hi>Erwin</hi> of <hi>Scotland:</hi> their works will teſtify ſufficiently: Yet if you deſire to know the conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient opinion of the Proteſtant Divines, take <hi>Calvin</hi> in his 25. Sect. of his 4. book of <hi>Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions; Beza</hi> in his expoſition on the 13. to to the <hi>Rom.</hi> and the <hi>Harmony</hi> of them all, in the confeſſion of the <hi>Helvetian</hi> Divines in the 19. Sect. Article 25. They have prepared againſt <hi>Sophiſtications</hi> in their <hi>Anathema:</hi> there is put in both the <hi>palam</hi> and the <hi>Arte</hi> too, whoſoever openly by <hi>offence,</hi> as well as cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly pretending <hi>defence</hi> ſhall do it, there
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:170447:26"/>is a <hi>damnamus</hi> paſt upon him, there is ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence given by the <hi>Church</hi> againſt him, acquit him who will.</p>
            <p>Theſe are men whoſe names will tell you never were yet ſuſpected for a <hi>Malignant</hi> Party: Should we blot out theſe from the Catalogue of the <hi>Churchy,</hi> I fear we had but a poor <hi>Charter</hi> for our <hi>Religion;</hi> if we eſteem them as they are, <hi>Protestants,</hi> I wonder how we can make ſo brave a flouriſh with this late taken <hi>Proteſtation</hi> in our hats, and ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh the genuine interpretation from our hearts.</p>
            <p>If then there be any here with whom that ſacred name of <hi>Majeſty,</hi> like a high Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain at a great diſtance, has ſeemed to va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh into the Air and prove a little nothing, ſuffer your ſelves to be undeceived; ſearch the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> and if ye be of <hi>Davids</hi> faith put on <hi>Davids</hi> conſcience, who after he had cut off the skirt of <hi>Saul's</hi> robe privily, his heart ſmote him, and his tears waſh'd out his faule: 1 <hi>Samuel</hi> 24.6, <hi>The Lord forbid that I ſhould do this thing, unto my Maſter the Lords Anointed, to ſtretch forth my hand a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, ſeeing he is the anointed of the Lord:</hi> He did but <hi>cut off a lap,</hi> and ſhall we lay our Lords anointed <hi>naked?</hi> Naked, not to relieve his wants; naked, to diſcover (if any were) his ſhames. If we be <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> it makes
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:170447:26"/>good our title to him he is <hi>Chriſtus Domini, The Lords Chriſt:</hi> if we be <hi>Proteſants</hi> (I ſpeak it again) ſuch as diſclaiming the names of <hi>Papists,</hi> would not degenerate into their <hi>Religion,</hi> we muſt confeſs that <hi>damnation is the portion of him that reſists this ordinance of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Shall <hi>Iſaiah</hi> call <hi>Cyrus</hi> the Lords <hi>anointed? Baruch</hi> and <hi>Jeremiah</hi> bid us pray for <hi>Nebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chodonoſer? Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> command ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to <hi>Tyberius, Nero</hi> and <hi>Caligula,</hi> all heatheniſh perſecuting <hi>Emperors?</hi> and we neglect our <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> our <hi>Theodeſius,</hi> the <hi>dew</hi> of Heaven which is fallen upon, this <hi>fleece</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> when all the World is <hi>wet</hi> with blood beſides? If we ſhall abuſe his patience into fury, can we expect any leſs judgment then to be forced under that fury to practiſe Patience? If any then neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting the <hi>Urim</hi> and the <hi>Prophets,</hi> the eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſht ordinance of God, as fanatick <hi>Saul</hi> did 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 28. and recurr to <hi>Wizards,</hi> (wiſe women, as you call them) and inquire of them the event of ſuch a battle, as this would prove; they may perhaps bring you to <hi>Samuels</hi> Ghoſt, ſome <hi>Devill</hi> in a <hi>Prophets</hi> likeneſs, but look for no better ſucceſs, then he fourd there, the death of your ſelves and your Sons, The ſtars in their courſe from Heaven will fight againſt <hi>Siſera, &amp; conjura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:170447:27"/>venient in claſſca venti,</hi> the wind and the <hi>hail-ſtones</hi> will muſter up their forces againſt <hi>Adonizedek</hi> and his confederates. But for you which deſpiſe <hi>Micah</hi> and his private new fangled <hi>devotion,</hi> which reſiſt <hi>Dan,</hi> and his riotous, tumultuous <hi>aſſemblies,</hi> which would cool <hi>Benjamin,</hi> and his goatiſh rave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous <hi>luſt,</hi> make it your care to continue a <hi>Rex in Iſrael.</hi> Suffer no <hi>Baanahs</hi> and <hi>Rechabs</hi> that dare murther <hi>Kings</hi> there beds, no <hi>Bigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans</hi> and <hi>Tharezes</hi> that dare entertain the motion in their hearts, to live amongſt you: <hi>Oyles</hi> by experience we know will mix, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though power'd into a veſſel, much water be put betwixt them: You which have found the <hi>Oyle</hi> of the <hi>holy Spirit</hi> in your hearts, let it joyne your hearts and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mix your ſouls to the <hi>Oyle</hi> upon the head of Gods <hi>anointed:</hi> That thus the religion of your <hi>hearts</hi> may burſt our of joyfull <hi>lips</hi> with prayers, <hi>That God would viſit him as he did</hi> Moſes <hi>in the buſh,</hi> Joſhua <hi>in the Battell,</hi> Gide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>in the field,</hi> David <hi>in the Temple: that the dew of his abundant mercies may fall upon his head, and that he would give unto him the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings of</hi> David <hi>and</hi> Solomon: <hi>That he would he his helmet of Salvation againſt the face of all his enemies and a ſtrong Tower of defence in the time of adverſity: That his raign may be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperous, and his dayes many; That peace and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:170447:27"/>love, holyneſſe, and Juſtice, and Truth, all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain Vertues may flouriſh in his time: That his people may ſerve him with Honour and Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, and that he may ſo duly ſerve God here on Earth that he may hereafter everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly raign with God in Heaven.</hi> Amen. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:170447:28"/>
            <head>The Second SERMON.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:170447:28"/>
                  <hi>JUDGES 4.23.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>Curſe ye <hi>Meroz</hi> (ſaid the Angel of the Lord) yea, curſe ye bitterly the Inhabitants thereof: becauſe they came not to the help of the Lord againſt the mighty.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Text no doubt in ſeaſon; we have an age to <hi>Curſe</hi> in, <hi>I</hi> to <hi>curſe bitterly</hi> too <hi>tanquam venena Aſpidum,</hi> the poyſon of Aſpes is under our lips. And theſe lips we think are touched by the <hi>Angel of God</hi> too: A coal from the Altar at leaſt has fired our tongues: Nay we are grown valiant of late, we dare go out to <hi>fight</hi> now and make the people believe, it is <hi>to the help of the Lord:</hi> And that no title be left out, 'tis <hi>to the help the Lord against the mighty too:</hi> Our pulpits by their Almighty power can cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate new forces, and in one nights ſpace pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim them mighty whom our Saterdays night Pamphlets told us where to be pittied for their weakneſs: Thus can we wreſt the Scripture to our own deſtruction, and gain this credit when we are once unmaskt, that we have been plauſible deceivers.</p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:170447:29"/>
            <p>'Tis no new rule, that <hi>corruptio optima fit peſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma,</hi> That the moſt Sovereign antidote when the Spirits are decay'd, or that it ſelf by ſome unskilfull Emperick miſ-apply'd proves of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes the rankeſt poyſon; And <hi>I</hi> know indigefting ſtomachs may corrupt the moſt nouriſhing meats, and the ſweeteſt flowers may ſtink of his breath that ſmells them: Thus that pure, that ſacred fountain of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scripture, whence the waters of life are drawn in their own Chriſtall integrity, when it is royld with our inventions proves <hi>aqua mortis,</hi> the poyſon'd waters of <hi>Sodom:</hi> The ſtanding lake which neither, flows to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Contryes nor nouriſhes in their own: <hi>tuus eſſe incipit.</hi> This book of God, ſo abuſed does God as little or leſs ſervice, then the <hi>Turkiſh Alcoran</hi> or the old <hi>Romane-Tables. I</hi> know this place was never meant for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſy: The intent of Sermons was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, for concluſions to edification, not for diſputation; they ſhould not rob the chair. But yet when <hi>Sheba</hi> ſhall dare to blow the <hi>Trumpet</hi> in the high-way and renounce his inheritance in <hi>David,</hi> 'tis time for <hi>Joab</hi> to caſt a bank about his City and beſiege him: If any unprejudicate and well-affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Chriſtians, have drank in poyſon at their ears, which now <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, inflames their ſouls, ſets them a fire on miſchief; <hi>I</hi>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:170447:29"/>ſhall deſire (which <hi>I</hi> do on my knees to heaven) by a plain leſſon on <hi>Deboras</hi> harp to diſenchant them, and by a true though home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly relation of this ſtory here, a relation in which neither language nor method ſhall be conciſe, to undeceive them.</p>
            <p>The people of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> Gods own inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance was at this time under the govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their <hi>Judges,</hi> which had then the ſupream authority. Which authority, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it were the ſame with what their <hi>Kings</hi> did after injoy, or onely a praeparative to it, an Uſher to the royall dignity, I will not here determine. Yet this <hi>I</hi> am ſure of, it came from Heaven, and God himſelf was Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of it; for when the common people, <hi>(queis ſemper mutare potentes principium eſt,)</hi> whoſe brains are alwaies turning round up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their changes, did in the following ſtory deſire a <hi>King</hi> (which might ſeem an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable and fair exchange, whether ye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard their higher credit with other nations, or their greater ſecurity againſt forraign powers, or the praedetermination of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, who had promiſed this digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty long ago to the ſeed of <hi>Abraham Gen.</hi> 17.) God takes the affront as put upon himſelf 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18. <hi>They have not refuſed thee, but they have refuſed me that I ſhould not raign over them:</hi> So conſtant is Almighty God to his
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:170447:30"/>own principles, that although in things in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended by himſelf, he will not be prevented by the phantaſtick deſires of men.</p>
            <p>Well! <hi>Iſrael</hi> thus founded had many ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies: furnaces at leſt to cleanſe them from their droſs: <hi>Inteſtina pericula,</hi> pills left in the bowels of their poſſeſſions to purge out their corruption: Five Lords of the <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtines,</hi> and the <hi>Zidonians</hi> and the <hi>Hivites</hi> and the <hi>Jebuſites</hi> and the <hi>Perizzites</hi> and the <hi>Canaanites,</hi> who would claim title of inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance to this land of promiſe. Amongſt theſe, <hi>Jabin</hi> a Mighty Man (that had nine hunderd Chariots of Iron, and a powerfull hoſt, whoſe Captain was <hi>Siſera,</hi> that lived in <hi>Haroſheth,</hi>) like a near neighbour, he lies heavy on them; he oppreſſeth, the Sons of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Thoſe which would ſhew their skill in fetching proper names from their origin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, (and indeed your old <hi>Geneva</hi> Bibles do it) tell me that <hi>Siſera</hi> ſignifies a <hi>foreſeer of Horſes,</hi> and <hi>Haroſheth</hi> a <hi>wooden place of ſtrength;</hi> once get a <hi>place of strength,</hi> and then pretend ſome <hi>fears</hi> and <hi>jealouſies</hi> of <hi>I</hi> know not what impoſſible conceits, that naked <hi>Iſrael</hi> (which <hi>had not a ſpeare among forty thouſand</hi> in the beginning of this Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter) is preparing ſtrength of Horſes, or <hi>I</hi> know not what, 'tis provocation enough for <hi>Siſera</hi> to go up againſt them.</p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:170447:30"/>
            <p>Their judge <hi>Deborah</hi> (a Woman of moſt maſculine Spirit) was under a Palme tree, in the highway to Mount <hi>Ephraim:</hi> Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther excluded her City or not, I cannot tell, but the text ſayes there ſhe dwelt: And truly why may we not think excluded? 'Twas <hi>Davids</hi> lot afterward, who had more Majeſty and title too, in and to the Royal City, which himſelf had raiſed; yet forced from thence, <hi>Bahurim</hi> and the other places as he paſſed by, proves as ungratefull as <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem</hi> her ſelf. She with her Co-partner <hi>Barak,</hi> at the Lords appointment do prepare for Battle: But alas <hi>niſi Dominus</hi> — unleſſe the Lord had been on their ſide, all the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces they could gather had not been enough for <hi>Siſeras</hi> hoſt to breath themſelves upon. <hi>Reuben</hi> they finde divided, <hi>Gilead</hi> would not paſs his borders: <hi>Aſher</hi> had poſſeſſed himſelf of the Sea Coaſts and the ſtrong holds, he thought himſelf ſecurer there: <hi>Dan</hi> was imployed about the ſhips, he will make the coaſts ſure, whatſoever becomes of the Countrey within: Yes, <hi>naviget Anty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceras,</hi> a little Hellebore would purge his brain better and make him wiſer. Onely the two <hi>Northern</hi> Tribes <hi>Zebulon</hi> and <hi>Napthali,</hi> with ten thouſand men which offer themſelves willingly will undertake this quarrell. Yet let me not beſpatter all the reſt: <hi>Ephraim,</hi>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:170447:31"/>and <hi>Benjamin,</hi> and <hi>Machir</hi> the ſon of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſes,</hi> and <hi>Iſſachar</hi> too, all <hi>Southern</hi> Counties ſent out ſome <hi>Nobles,</hi> which were ſo bold as to be honeſt, and aſſociated themſelves in this holy war. And I know not how there crept in ſome that handle the pen of the writer too, which might make Gods battails famous, and record to after ages thoſe ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries which the ſword here had wrote in blood. Thoſe <hi>Judges</hi> which eſcaped the noiſe of the Archers <hi>came down upon their white Aſſes:</hi> and although the <hi>Laws</hi> are mute where the <hi>Drum</hi> ſpeaks, they durſt then tell them what the Law was, they durſt ſit in Judgment, and ſpeake the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous acts of God. As for the reſt, they choſe them new Gods, (<hi>novum cultum</hi> ſaith the Paraphraſer) new forms of devotion, new moulds of the old Religion, if you will; eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one made an Idoll of himſelf and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped his own inventions.</p>
            <p>Well, their Army thus confederate pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare their march: But where is their Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munition? No armour but that of faith: not one ſhield or ſpeare amongſt forty thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand men in <hi>Iſrael:</hi> and as little hopes of ſupplyes was there in other places: <hi>Aſher</hi> had ſtop'd the coaſts, <hi>Dan</hi> had ſeized the Ships, the high wayes were beſet, and the travellers glad to walk thorough by paths.
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:170447:31"/>But <hi>Deborah</hi> aroſe, <hi>Deborah</hi> that mother in <hi>Iſrael:</hi> She knew that Gods hand was not ſhortned that he could not redeem, nor his power diminiſhed that he could not deliver: <hi>Joſhua</hi> had tryed it before with trumpets of rams-hornes, <hi>Ehud</hi> with his two edged ſword, <hi>Shamgar</hi> with his ox-goad: He which before had ſlain five Kings with hailſtones, could not he muſter up an army of ſtars to fight in their courſes againſt the army of <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſera? Timere metuit:</hi> tis the Lords appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſhe dares not fear it, but marches on couragiouſly, whilſt her generall <hi>Barak</hi> leads on the forces, to Mount <hi>Tabor</hi> the randevouz. A little diſtance from the Mountain was the village <hi>Meroz,</hi> whoſe neighbouring Situation might well have ſuccored them, if not with a greater ſtrength of men for a reſerve at need, yet with a neceſſary ſhelter in the day of Battle: But this, whether affrighted with the chariots, or truſting to the horſes of the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies troops, ſhut in themſelves and ſhut out the Iſraelites <hi>they will not come to hely the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And indeed what need of help has he, in whoſe name all help conſiſts? The battle joynes; the Charets are diſcomfited, <hi>Siſera</hi> leaves his Coach and flies away on foot: and <hi>Deborah</hi> returns back a triumphant Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queror. Yet leaſt She ſhould forget that God that <hi>taught her hands to fight, and her armes
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:170447:32"/>to break thoſe bows of ſteel.</hi> She ſings a <hi>Paean,</hi> a ſong which a Quire of Angels would Eccho too, a ſong of triumph to the Lord of hoſts: In the midſt of which, as it were a ſharp, a reliſh to all the reſt, ſhe brands this ingratitude of <hi>Meroz</hi> in the Text. <hi>Curſe ye Meroz (ſayes the Angel) curſe ye bitterly the inhabitants thereof, becauſe they came not to the help of the Lord, to the help of the Lord againſt the mighty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall be very brief in the Theory of my Text. Diſcourſes of this nature require more practiſe: In the words behold an <hi>Anathema,</hi> a ſentence of excommunication (if you will) pronounced: And accordingly to make it legal, here are all the parts of it: 1. There is the hand and ſeal, the authority confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it, <hi>The Angel ſayes it,</hi> 2. There is the form of the ſentence, <hi>curſe ye; yea curſe ye bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly:</hi> 3. There is the Excommunicate per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, <hi>Meroz and her inhabitants:</hi> 4. There is the crime of which ſhe ſtands convict, a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative fault, a ſin of omiſſion, <hi>for not helping the Lord, not helping the Lord againſt the mighty:</hi> Oppoſitions ſeem here at the firſt view abundantly to meet: The ark of God and Dagon you would think were content with the ſame roof: here is the Angel of God, that meſſenger of glad tidings, with curſes in his mouth: heres God the Lord Almighty has need of help againſt the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:170447:32"/>mighty: here is the firſt <hi>Caos</hi> moulded up together, yet with your patience, out of this darkneſs God may inable us to produce ſome light.</p>
            <p>Firſt the <hi>Angel</hi> ſpeaks it; and well there is ſo good authority. If this blazing ſtarr from Heaven, had not pointed out this judgment, holy <hi>Deborah</hi> would have bleſſed her enemies, and prayed for them that uſed her thus deſpitefully. I will not trouble you here with the Schoolmens quarrels what this <hi>Angels</hi> name was, or of what <hi>Order</hi> in the Heavens, whether he defended viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, or <hi>motu Angelico,</hi> inſenſibly: pretty cob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>webs theſe are to catch flies in. Or whether this <hi>Angel</hi> were her confederate. <hi>Barak,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired by Heaven with a Prophetick ſoul, which <hi>Peter Martyr</hi> thinks a probable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecture: be it one or other <hi>in idem res rediit,</hi> this we know, that in times paſt there was a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> divers wayes and manners, how God ſpoake to our fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers by the Prophets: <hi>Saul</hi> (it ſeems) 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 28, Made tryal of them all, he ſought God by dreams and viſions, by <hi>Urim</hi> and the Prophets, but finding Heaven inflex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ible, <hi>Acheronta movet,</hi> a witch at <hi>Endor</hi> muſt do the feat, and raiſe up the Divel in <hi>Samuels</hi> mantle to inform him: which <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cromantick</hi> Religion I would to God it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:170447:33"/>not down to theſe our dayes; Too many I fear me, finding their dreams grown ridiculous, and their viſions blinded, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daining the <hi>Urim,</hi> the pretious ſtones of the high Prieſts breaſtplate, and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, have but one refuge left, ſome old woman which can raiſe up <hi>Samuels</hi> Ghoſt, a Divil in a Prophets likeneſs, which without the wages of <hi>Balaak,</hi> or the expectation of an <hi>Angel</hi> of God, can make every Cup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boards ſide or tables-end the top of <hi>Piſgah,</hi> and the top of <hi>Peor,</hi> from whence they ſpit out their poyſon upon the hoſt of <hi>Iſrael: Nos autem Chriſtum non ſic didicimus,</hi> if any Man amongſt us be thus contentious we have no ſuch cuſtom nor the Church of Chriſt: <hi>Deborah</hi> was a Propheteſs yet durſt not ſhe ſtrain her authority thus farr: but <hi>ſignatim di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit,</hi> leaſt this curſe ſhould pretend to a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality and prove a leading caſe to all ſucceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ages, ſhe ſhews her patent and produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces her authority, <hi>The Angel of the Lord ſayes it.</hi> And let us give Gods <hi>Angel</hi> this honour to affoord him, 1. A <hi>Credendum</hi> 2. A <hi>Tremendum,</hi> 3. A <hi>Cavendum:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Credendum</hi> 1. Gods Angel is but his meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger, and ſhall God ſpeak it and the thing not come to paſs? Tis confirmation enough to me that <hi>Meroz</hi> fell under this bitter curſe, becauſe neither ſacred Scripture, nor hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:170447:33"/>writer that (I can find) did ever ſince make mention of it: And indeed Sirs, lets take heed; there are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Angels</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Earth ſtill: The Church has <hi>Angels</hi> ſaies St. <hi>John,</hi> and the Woman of <hi>Tekoah</hi> thought the King of <hi>Iſrael</hi> was at leaſt <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> as the <hi>Angel</hi> of the Lord: Thus when the <hi>Angel</hi> of the Church curſes ſhall our ſouls be ſo irreligiouſly incredulous as to call it <hi>brutum fulmen,</hi> a ſquib in the air, or if the Angel of the ſtate curſes, to call it <hi>fulmen br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ti, Hannibals</hi> fagots on his bulls hornes to make them roar the lowder? Experience will be a ſharp a Miſtriſs, when we ſhall one day feel the Burthen of that which we would not believe.</p>
            <p>But, 2. <hi>Tremendum. Manoahs</hi> Wife thought the face of the <hi>Angel</hi> very terrible, and at that time when he comes to comfort her <hi>Judges,</hi> 13. and ſhall not <hi>Meroz</hi> tremble when he comes to curſe her? This is moſt truly <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the Eclipſing of the Sun, the blacking over the face of Heaven. <hi>Vaenobis</hi> (ſaies St. <hi>Bernard</hi>) <hi>ſi quando provocati ſancti Angeli peccatis &amp; negligentiis, indignos nos judicaverint praeſentia &amp; vifitatione ſua.</hi> Unhappy <hi>Sodome</hi> when her daring ſins put <hi>Lot</hi> and his <hi>Angels</hi> to flight; but infinitely more unhappy, when they came armed with fire and brimſtone to deſtroy it. Our
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:170447:34"/>good God created them Miniſtring Spirits, partly for the uſe of Men, ore whom he gave them charge; though all that time he never leſſens their joys of Heaven, there is <hi>exterius Miniſterium,</hi> ſayes <hi>Gregory,</hi> but ſtill there is <hi>interior contemplatio:</hi> But when our guardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians prove our executioners, when the Sheepheards which ſhould quarrel with the wolves, devour the flock: when the <hi>Cherub</hi> that defends the garden of <hi>Eden,</hi> brandiſhes a flaming ſword to drive out <hi>Adam,</hi> let us fear and tremble.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, <hi>Cavendum:</hi> if we fear that <hi>curſe,</hi> beware that ſin which cauſed it: when <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nathan</hi> ſhoots an arrow o're <hi>Davids</hi> head, tis enough to make <hi>David</hi> fly the place, to beware his Fathers vvrath: Here is one ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row ſhot over us, and it lights on <hi>Meroz,</hi> but the bow is bent ſtill, and armed with as great a <hi>curſe,</hi> a <hi>curſe</hi> for <hi>curſing,</hi> if not for not <hi>going out to help the Lord,</hi> I am ſure for going <hi>to fight against the Lord:</hi> this vvas par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular here and occaſionall, the other is ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall and eternall. <hi>God</hi> ſpeaks that, the <hi>Angel</hi> of God ſpeaks this: <hi>Curſe ye Meroz (ſayes the Angel of the Lord) yea curſe yee bitterly the inhabitants thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We are novv come to the ſentence: <hi>Curſe yee, yea curſe ye bitterly,</hi> that is, <hi>curſe ye with a curſing,</hi> in the originall: in vvhich I
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:170447:34"/>will not ſo farr intereſt my ſelf, as to think to teach you, that it is a <hi>Hebraiſme:</hi> yet thus far give me leave to note, that theſe ingeminations are either uſed <hi>aſſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erando,</hi> as a note of confirmation, as that in <hi>Geneſis</hi> 2. <hi>in the day thou eateſt thereof thou ſhalt ſurely dye, moriendo morieris;</hi> or <hi>intendendo,</hi> as a ſcrew to ſet it higher, as this here, <hi>execratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus execramini, curſe ye bitterly.</hi> What a curſe is I ſhall ſatisfie my ſelf, and you too <hi>I</hi> hope, in a plain Narration from <hi>Aquihas: Idem eſt maledicere</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>&amp; malum di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere,</hi> in his 76. <hi>Question</hi> 2.2. curſing is the ſame, with ſpeaking or wiſhing evill: And ſo a man may curſe as many wayes as he ſpeaks: which is either <hi>Enuntiative,</hi> decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring what is done: Thus <hi>Deborah</hi> in this ſong may be ſaid to curſe <hi>Siſera,</hi> in that Rhetorical <hi>Cataſtrophe</hi> which <hi>Jael</hi> brought upon his life, <hi>At her feet he bowed, he fell, he lay down; at her feet, he bowed, he fell, where he bowed there he fell down dead:</hi> or 2ly <hi>Imperative</hi> by commanding what ſhould be done, which none, can challenge but they which have ſoveraignty, as God or his Meſſengers, like the Angell here; or 3ly <hi>Optative,</hi> by wiſhing what might be done, as <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> moſt execrations are. The firſt is in it ſelf indifferent, neither good nor evil, unleſſe detraction accompany it;
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:170447:35"/>The two laſt are alwayes evill unleſſe ſome occaſion of a greater good do invite them: And this good is double, 1. Either that of juſtice; thus God may curſe <hi>immundum mundum,</hi> the unclean World: <hi>Eliſha</hi> may curſe the reviling brats; and the Church may curſe the baſtard of spring of Sectaries, which like the Mices birthday, fill the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain with abundant ſqueeking in the bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth, but then <hi>naſcuntur ridiculi,</hi> you may know they are empty veſſels becauſe they ſound ſo much; or ſecondly the good of profit, that affliction may reduce them: As <hi>David Pſal.</hi> 9. wiſht a <hi>terror upon the Nations that they might know themſelves to be but men.</hi> From hence then we ſhall receive a ſpeedy ſatisfaction, to thoſe three que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, which are only material, 1. <hi>penes quos eſt,</hi> in whoſe power this power of cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing lies, 2. <hi>ad quos attinet,</hi> on whoſe ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders it will fall; 3. <hi>in quantum praevalet,</hi> with what burthen it preſſes: there is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite diſtance between all theſe: here is <hi>abyſſus abyſſum invocans,</hi> one deep calling upon another; only a powerfull hand from heaven can throw down vengeance, only a ſinners neck can bear it, and if this thunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolt be not ſtopt only the pit of hell can bound it. From heaven it comes, whether immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately from God himſelf, or from his Dele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gates:
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:170447:35"/>The firſt can make that ſerpent lick the duſt of the earth, which but juſt now aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pired to the Scepter of Heaven: he can make <hi>Cain</hi> a Runnegate in his own land, and fear the ſtroak of death from man, when he and his father ſummed up [for ought we know] the total number of mankind. The other have it by Commiſſion and that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, they had need take care ſhould be well ſigned, or elſe their arrows will recoyl upon their own boſoms, and they will provoke God to bleſſe by their malitious curſes. Some good expoſitors are of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, that all the curſes denounced in the old <hi>Law</hi> ſhall rather be interpreted for <hi>propheticae praedictiones,</hi> then <hi>imprecationes maledicae:</hi> But what ever power they had, I am ſure 'tis now limited; there is an <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangelical</hi> temper if we believe Chriſt that ſpeaks it; when <hi>James</hi> and <hi>John</hi> would have been a flaſhing in the clouds, and followed <hi>Elias</hi> in the <hi>Law,</hi> for fire from Heaven on the Village of the <hi>Samaritans: Christ</hi> cooles their furious zeal with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Spirit, <hi>Luke</hi> 9. he rebukes them ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>ye know not what manner of Spirits ye are of:</hi> Fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bear ſuch legal threats, if you follow me your Maſter, I came to ſave the World not to deſtroy it. For <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nias</hi> and <hi>Saphira's</hi> judgment, 'tis true it
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:170447:36"/>came from heaven; but unleſſe you en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terline the Text and read it with ſpecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles to make it bigger, it will no way appear to be cauſed by <hi>Peters</hi> Curſe. So that if we compare St. <hi>Pauls</hi> precept, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. <hi>bleſſe and curſe not,</hi> with his <hi>anathematizing</hi> Text, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16. we ſhall ſoon find the Church has no keyes left to ſhut up Heaven but thoſe which <hi>Chriſt</hi> left, as a Legacy in that ſacred ordination of his Apoſtles.</p>
            <p>But ſecondly this curſe is only due for ſin, that being the adequate object of the wrath of God: Hence does St. <hi>Paul</hi> think <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> doing good, will be an undoubted ſhield againſt the power: So that <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines, Uteunque ferit,</hi> will prove but a blunt puſh, his excommunication undeſerved is but a bull without hornes, crackers ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon a line; flaſh they may, but wound they cannot. Laſtly to Hell it goes if not prevented: The Royall prophet in the 37. <hi>Pſalm</hi> ſayes that, <hi>they that be curſed of God ſhall be cut off: Cut off</hi> from the Earth firſt, as <hi>Pharoah</hi> and his crew of perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, (after they had blunted the arrows of God with often wounding, though they could never yet pierce their hardned hearts:) his final deſtruction is threatned, <hi>Exod</hi> 9.15. <hi>he will cut them off from the face of the Earth:</hi> But 2. <hi>cut them down</hi>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:170447:36"/>or a paſſage for them down to hell too; witneſs <hi>Corah</hi> and his rebellious Conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, <hi>quibus dum non eſſent digni vivere</hi> [ſayes <hi>Optatus</hi>] <hi>nec mori conceſſum eſt:</hi> not deſerving to live, they were not vouchſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed to dye: <hi>ſepulti ſunt priuſquam mortui:</hi> they which had made a ſeperation from their Fathers, may not be ſuffered to be gathered to their Fathers, but go down quick to Hell. This is the effect of a <hi>curſe,</hi> a <hi>curſe</hi> ariſing from a juſt <hi>cauſe,</hi> proceeding from a juſt <hi>Judge:</hi> If this be the cauſe of <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roz,</hi> let her beware, and ſure it is, for her <hi>judge</hi> is juſt that ſpeaks it, the <hi>Angel</hi> ſayes, <hi>Curſe ye Meroz and her inhabitants.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We are come to the Perſons upon whom the cenſure falls, <hi>Meroz and her inhabitants:</hi> Where I will not make you ſport to tell you what pains <hi>Rupert</hi> takes (although he cite <hi>St. Hierom</hi> for it) to make <hi>Meroz</hi> the praeſident <hi>Angel</hi> of the <hi>Canaanites,</hi> and the inhabitants to be the people under his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection. <hi>Gerrae germanae,</hi> it is not worth confuting: Here is no Labyrinth that needs a clue, or if there did, expoſitors with one mouth aſſure me, that this village <hi>Meroz</hi> was a place adjoyning to the field of battle, which muſt now be made <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a <hi>piaculum,</hi> a ſacrifice to Gods curſe to expi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate the degenerate backwardneſs of the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:170447:37"/>neutrall tribes. Well may the gates of the Temple be made of Cedar trees; Cedars ſo fat, ſo joyfull, all Hieroglyphicks of Gods mercy; when as the gates of Heaven (for ought we find here) were open to an offending multitude, and only ſhut againſt this handfull of the people: Thus God is pleaſed ſometimes to decimate his male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factors, <hi>in paucos vindicta tranſit, in plures monitio,</hi> he ſets up <hi>Lots</hi> Wife as a pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſayes the <hi>Scholiast,</hi> a Trophie to turn the hearts of the back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſliding generations: for as he is a fire to burn the chaff, ſo he is a fan to ſeparate it from the purer wheat. When fawning <hi>Abſolom</hi> had ſeduced the people to a great rebellion, promiſing a freer courſe of juſtice if he might raign, 'tis true a ſlaughter of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> was made in the wood of <hi>Ephraim,</hi> but ſtill the ſurviving rebels were ſuffered to return with <hi>David,</hi> whilſt the juſtice of God contented it ſelf with the head of <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolom,</hi> hanging now as his counſels formerly had done, between Heaven and Hell. But ſtill as <hi>Meroz</hi> was but <hi>one</hi> place, yet a <hi>place</hi> it was, and a place very conſiderable: With great diſadvantage muſt <hi>Deborah</hi> fight, when the villages about her were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faederate with her enemies: Put caſe that God had defeated her before her enemy (as
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:170447:37"/>indeed <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c. A juſt cauſe does not alwayes inherit victory) what place was left to retreat to from the bloody Mountain? what refreſhment could be given to the fainting Souldiers? What diſheart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning found the remoter tribes, when the place they marched to, for freſh ſupplies up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on occaſion, proved the quarters of their enemies? As God gives to Men, ſo he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts from Men their opportunities: <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hekah</hi> was known to be a fit wife for <hi>Iſaac</hi> by her ready letting down her pitcher; and that ſoul that would be eſpouſed to Chriſt, muſt diſcover it ſelf by a ſeaſonable and willing ſervice. Yet mark, one ſtep farther yet, together with the inhabitants, <hi>Meroz</hi> herſelf, the very fabrick bears a burthen in the curſe. <hi>The Eagles nest is brought down from the Stars that the young ones may be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed: Oba.</hi> 4. Thus when by Gods per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> (accurſed for one mans pillaging) found a repulſe at the great City <hi>Aie,</hi> at the ſecond aſſault <hi>Joſhua</hi> contents not himſelf with the head of the ruler, or the throats of the Citizens, but makes the place it ſelf a deſolation. And this judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment God ſends down ſometimes upon the inanimate Creature, either becauſe it hath been the inſtrument to occaſion mans folly, or rather that his folly may be puniſht by
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:170447:38"/>that judgment; that man may learn to groan for ſin, by the Creaturs example, which grones under that puniſhment which is due to the ſin of man: Well may the young Eagles cry when the ones ſacriledg has fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the neſt ſhe builds in: 'tis the peoples ſins begets the Cities curſe: Thats the laſt part, the cauſe of this excommunication denounc'd, <hi>Curſe ye Meroz (ſayes the Angel) and her inhabitants, becauſe they went not out, to help the Lord, to help the Lord against the mighty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And indeed when God himſelf is gone up with a ſhout, and the Lord with the ſound of the trumpet, he may curſe himſelf that ſtayes behind: If it be true that God does purſue thoſe whom he doth not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company, it is more true that he comes back upon thoſe that do not accompany him. Gods cauſe is ours, in which if we will not bear a ſhare, we ſhall ſurely bear the burthen. When the <hi>Reubenites</hi> and the <hi>Gadites,</hi> (whether tired out with their tedious march, or allured with the fatneſs of the plains of the <hi>Gileadites,</hi> or affrighted with their Brethrens reports of the enemies ſtrength fron the valley of <hi>Eſchol</hi>) were now grown lazy and neglected the portion of the other tribes, deſiring, as they thought to ſleep in a whole skin, and not to endan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:170447:38"/>themſelves by paſſing over <hi>Jordan:</hi> See what a conteſtation <hi>Moſes</hi> himſelf under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes: <hi>Numb.</hi> 32. What a ſtrife beget they in meekneſs! He which chid his own paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons before, now fell to reviling them: They were <hi>nigri Jovis incrementum,</hi> an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of ſinfull men, the fomentors of Gods anger: And accordingly was their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward: The firſt and greateſt Giant <hi>Og,</hi> muſt be their task to tame; and the <hi>Gileadites</hi> once cleared, unleſs they will go armed before the Lord to warr and help their Brethren, intrench themſelves as ſure as they can, they ſhall never ſhut out a boſom enemy: there ſins will find them out.</p>
            <p>But ſtay; can God want help? will he, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſufficient of himſelf for Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth, flie to man for ſuccour, in whom there is no help? What new <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phoeus</hi> have we upon the Earth, which drives the Heavenly powers to the banks of <hi>Nile</hi> for refuge! Is not God <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Almighty? Whoſe Lips are the fountains of power, at the breath of whoſe noſtrils the infernall ſpirits tremble? and ſhall he want aſſiſtance againſt the mighty? Tis true; and yet he ſo diſpoſes his affairs on Earth, That man may ſometimes ſeem to get the upper hand: God works not all things by a miraculous power but lets
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:170447:39"/>out ſome part of his vineyard to the til<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage and husbandry of man; in which ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, <hi>depopulatur aper,</hi> the wild boars have their lurking holes, and the little foxes have their boroughs: force or cunning have broken down their hedges. He ſometimes permits a reviling <hi>Shimei</hi> in the face of <hi>Davids</hi> Army: a ſacrelegious rout to deface his Sanctuary, and not bury them in the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ines which they make: a <hi>Jewiſh confedera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,</hi> which <hi>Turciſme</hi> would ſtand amazed at to recrucifie our Saviour <hi>in imagine,</hi> and hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto not payes them home with <hi>Judas</hi> his portion, to go hang themſelves.</p>
            <p>And theſe the all ſeeing eye of providence diſpenſes, whether the more ſurely to prove his friends, or the more fully to confound ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. For the firſt, God hath a ſtorehouſe, from whence he could fil the hands of al his mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers yet leaves he ſome hungry, ſome thirſty, ſome naked, to ſee who would refreſh them: <hi>Non quod te indiget, ſed quod te <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o indige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re cupit,</hi> he has no need of thee, but he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires that thou ſhouldeſt have need of him: What needed 32000 men of <hi>Iſrael</hi> gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed under <hi>Gideons</hi> ſtandart, when 300 did the feat? But to try who would ſtand up for the Lord, and who will bow their knees to drink of the waters: who would adore the flowing Tranſitory pleaſures here. 'Tis true
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:170447:39"/>in temporall as well as eternall ſalvation, <hi>qui te ſine te fecit, te ſine te non ſalvabit,</hi> he which created thee alone, requires thy own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence to thy preſervation: nay by this means God pulls off the vizard from the face of Hypocrytes, unguilds their garniſhed fron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlers, and leaves them as black as the ſin they flatter with, If it had not been for <hi>Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loms</hi> rebellion, who could prove <hi>Achitophel Davids</hi> privy Counſellour had been a traitor? Who would have thought <hi>Amaſa,</hi> honoured by <hi>David</hi> with the name of Cozen, one of his bone and of his fleſh, would have ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted of the generalſhip without <hi>Davids</hi> Commiſſion? Who could believe that <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> that Royall City, honoured with <hi>Davids Throne,</hi> not ſubſiſting (as it ſeems) two Moneths without his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, would have gone up after <hi>Abſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lom?</hi> This is the Divine Eye of Wiſdom which can produce ſound fruit from ſuch rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſtocks.</p>
            <p>In the ſecond there is the ſupream hand of power; when wicked deſigns proſper ſo happily that they are gathered into a head, till with one ſtroke God cuts them off: as <hi>Jehu</hi> ſerves the Prieſts of <hi>Baal</hi> 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 10: Pretends a ſolemn ſacrifice, invites them with a full ceremony, cloaths them with the richeſt veſtments, makes a holy day
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:170447:40"/>feaſt for <hi>Baals</hi> worſhipers: The day was theirs, and the Prophets of God were look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon as poor inferiour humble Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; but in the midſt of their triumph, fourſcore men made it end in a bloody ſacrifice, they are all cut off, not one eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capes. The Servants of the houſhold could have weeded out the tares, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13. But it was the Maſters policy to let them grow ripe before he burnt them: They would make the greater blaze: God Almighty, I know, could have routed out the tares of hereſie, the tares of ſedition, which in theſe dayes of ſin have almoſt overtopped the ſtanding wheat: but (I perſwade my ſelf) out of mercy to his Church, he has let them grow to theſe licentious times, when every Son of <hi>Belial,</hi> dares openly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover his untutor'd ſpirit, when we find more <hi>ſects,</hi> then ſome years ſince we thought our Church had nouriſh'd <hi>Sectaries,</hi> that the ſword of juſtice now knowing them, may make the ſurer &amp; ſharper ſtroke againſt them: <hi>Babels</hi> confuſion had not been ſo remarke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, but that the tower was raiſed ſo high as that it ſtood a pillar to after ages: The weakneſs of <hi>Deborahs</hi> forces and <hi>Jabins</hi> ſtrength enlarge Gods honour: he gets a name by <hi>pulling down the mighty from their ſeat;</hi> but ſtill he is ſenſible of the falſe heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:170447:40"/>cowardiſe of the backſliding troops: He <hi>curſes Merox and her inhabitants becauſe they came not forth to help the Lord, to help the Lord againſt the mighty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have made haſt, you ſee with, the plain-ſong of my text, that I may ſpend ſome time in the deſcant, in which every one of us muſt bear a part: And I cannot but begin with a juſt indignation againſt thoſe who have abuſed the words and made them ſpeak their own crazy humours, and frantick dreams. Like Men troubled with an <hi>Hydrophobia,</hi> bitten with a mad dog, and now raging, they think all things before them look like water, like the froth of their own brains: Indeed Scripture ſhall be no longer <hi>Scripture,</hi> if it do not pleaſe them: Being in this like the old <hi>Tyrians,</hi> who were wont to whip their Gods if they croſſed them with a misfortune, till they made them better: Thus came they armed to the Pulpit with as brave a reſolution as <hi>Hannibal</hi> to the <hi>Alps, aut viam invenient aut facient?</hi> Where they find no tracke before them they will adventure firſt; and are grown ſo daringly preſumptuous as to ſlight theſe texts which, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> do in plain rerms croſs their trayterous poſition, and tell you it was doctrine fit for thoſe times the Apoſtles lived in, (I my ſelf have heard it)
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:170447:41"/>were they upon the Earth now, when Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians knew their own ſtrength, they would write in another ſtrain. Blaſphemous wretches! is the bleſſed Spirit of God a ſervant or the times; Is that eternal goodneſſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, unchangeably conſtant, and for ever more the ſame, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the Idoll <hi>fortune,</hi> and dances he upon a wheel? Never <hi>Muſſelman</hi> thought thus of his lawgiver <hi>Mahomet,</hi> never <hi>Heathen</hi> of the rule of <hi>Nature.</hi> Yet that they may ſhew ſome commixture of madneſs and wit, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times they will prove ingeniouſly wicked, and like a conjurer caſt a miſt before your eyes, till you think you ſee the face of theſe times preſented you in the glaſs of prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie: which (once perſwaded) what ever language came from the top of <hi>Ebal,</hi> is a <hi>Charientiſmus,</hi> a meſſage of peace compared with theirs: Thus <hi>Deborah</hi> the <hi>Church</hi> ſhall fall a curſing <hi>Meroz</hi> the friends to the <hi>crown</hi> becauſe they came not out to help the Lord againſt <hi>Siſeras</hi> hoſt the <hi>royall Army.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: Here lets joyn hands: Good ſirs inſtruct me: whoſe perſon bore diſtreſſed <hi>Deborah?</hi> was it not the ſupream? and are there, or can there be 2. ſupreams? She was a Mother, a Judg, a Captain in <hi>Iſrael:</hi> And can any order that is <hi>a primo primus</hi> derived from the firſt be equall to it?
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:170447:41"/>Had <hi>Jabin</hi> been a King to <hi>Deborah</hi> I am ſure ſhe had too religious a ſoul to have curſed him: For what was <hi>Siſera?</hi> Was he not a ſtranger? One of another line, another claim, another religion, another God? one commanded by God long ſince to be expeld the Land, and his inheritance devided a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Tribes? Make you your ſelves an Analogy between the ſtories, and ſee what an apt proportion they have left. But one nice diſtinction will ſtop this gap: We can cut an hair between the <hi>King</hi> and his <hi>forces.</hi> The <hi>King</hi> is a good <hi>King,</hi> a well meaning <hi>King</hi> (and ſo he is in ſpite of their bold faced detractions) but his <hi>Siſeras,</hi> his <hi>Generals,</hi> his Commanders, they are none of ours: No, and yet within theſe three years, the reverend Fathers of our Church were quarreld at by theſe very Men for leaving their names out of our divine ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice book. But are we grown ſuch experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enced artificers to devide between the ſquir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel and the tail that hides the back? The fable makes a pretty dialogue between the wolf and the dog: The wolf bids him go home and ſleep quietly, why ſhould he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe himſelf to the winters froſts, and the ſummers heat, to watch his flock? There was no emnity between them: true (ſayes the dog) but when thou haſt worried my
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:170447:42"/>ſheep and art grown fat and luſty with their fleſh, thou maiſt ſeize upon my throat next.</p>
            <p>But cloſer yet: for I would faine follow my text, however they leave it: Neither has the <hi>Angel ſaid it</hi> to them, nor have they power to <hi>curſe,</hi> nor have they cutſed <hi>Meroz,</hi> nor curſe they <hi>for not helping of the Lord:</hi> nor (in their ſenſe) does the Lord need any help <hi>againſt the mighty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt an <hi>Angel</hi> has not ſaid it: whatever viſions they pretend: or if he ſhould, though an <hi>Angel</hi> from Heaven deliver any other doctrine then what the Scripture has preached <hi>let him be accurſed:</hi> I <hi>Gal.</hi> I. the Divine revelations and Angelicall deſcenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which the Anabaptiſts glory of, are things grown too naked to delude us any longer: They ſound like the ſtory of <hi>Mahomets</hi> dove. Since Chriſts aſcenſion into Heaven he left the holy Spirit as a Legacy to his Church; that Spirit which ſhall guide it into all truth; and ſo it will, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all theſe impoſtures: When their writings are <hi>ad thus &amp; ſcombros alligata,</hi> made as they are, waſtpaper: St. <hi>Peter</hi> and St. <hi>Paul</hi> will be true and ſound divinity: And yet <hi>I</hi> know tis no new thing for Satan to transform himſelf into an <hi>Angel</hi> of light, and become a lying Spirit in the
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:170447:42"/>mouths of ſuch as would be accounted Prophets: We know when he perſwaded a Nation to go to warr to its own deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: May our good God defend us from the like mischief.</p>
            <p>But 2ly. they have no power to <hi>curſe,</hi> no commiſſion for their execrations: a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans office is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.10. ſpeak friendly to their perſecutors: Marke the phraſe, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, well to them, and well of them too, not pump hell for language and arme the tongue with ſuch Rhetorick that it <hi>cutteth like a razor.</hi> The word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which the <hi>Septuagint</hi> uſes here for curſing, ſignifies <hi>pray ye barkward:</hi> (if ye will:) for ſo the <hi>Scholiaſt</hi> tels me that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the theme in <hi>Homers</hi> time ſignified humble prayers; but being abuſed in the ſucceeding ages who turned their <hi>prayers,</hi> into <hi>curſes,</hi> the interpretation of the word changed too and it ſignifide an execration: and indeed in this art of <hi>pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing backward</hi> we are too good proficients: If that be to pray we can learn our leſſons quickly: By the abuſe of time it comes that we have changed the genuine meaning of the word. For in the dayes of old, before Religion was adulterated, the reverend Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in the primitive times were wont to bleſs the patience of <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Souldiers: bleſs them for their loyalty, bleſs them for their
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:170447:43"/>ſervice performed to their moſt cruel blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſucking perſecutors: When they behaved themſelves like the ſtouteſt Champions in the cauſes of the Emperors, they were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged with an <hi>Euge ſic decet Chriſtianos</hi> you ſhew now that yee ſerve the Lord of Heaven, by obeying his <hi>vice-roys</hi> upon earth. But alas the ditty is chang'd in our dayes: if any true hearted piety dare be ſo bold as to ſtand in the juſt defence of that Soveraignty, which the law of God, the laws of Nations our oathes and proteſtations binds us to, there is an <hi>Ito maledicta</hi> paſſed upon it, it is <hi>curſed</hi> and <hi>curſed bitterly.</hi> But though they curſe yet God will bleſſe: It is not the name <hi>malignant</hi> can exclude us out of the Church <hi>triumphant,</hi> if in a true cauſe we are here <hi>militant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly it is not <hi>Meroz,</hi> any poor little Villages they curſe: <hi>tales aquilae muſcas non capiunt:</hi> but <hi>Tabor</hi> and <hi>Hermon</hi> the Mounts of God, the hills of Learning: God knows our <hi>Meroz's</hi> our Countrey pariſhes are infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuated with a bayard blindneſſe, they will neither ſee nor yet believe they are blind: Chyrurgions tell us no ſuch ſure ſign of death as a ſenſeleſſe <hi>Apathy,</hi> when we feel not the ſmarting of our wounds: Thus where our State is wounded, in the head, the ſeat of judgment, wounded in the heart,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:170447:43"/>the ſeat of life, wounded in the hands, the execution of juſtice, wounded in the feet, the interpretation of thoſe laws, on whoſe bottom the Kingdom ſtands, we as if we were bitten with a <hi>Tarantula,</hi> ſhall laugh our ſelves to death in the midſt of theſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtractions, and only be grieved at yeſterdays ache, and take phyſick for that diſeaſe which had ſeazed and left us three years a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goe. And this was the very caſe of the <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites</hi> in the great defection from <hi>Rhehobo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am,</hi> the complaint was oppreſſion by his Father <hi>Solomon,</hi> whoſe dayes indeed was golden dayes, the very ſtones of the ſtreet which the people trampled on, were outvyed (in their number almoſt) by others far more pretious: But crafty <hi>Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haboam</hi> galling their mindes firſt and then finding when it pinched, he ſcarrifies firſt, Remonſtrates to the people the greivous Yoke the King had thrown upon them, and then applies an itching plaiſter: he would eaſe them of the trouble to go up to worſhip at the Mother Church at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> he knew if the doors of the Sanctuary were o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, <hi>the law of God read there, would keep the people in ſubjection,</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 12.17. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he will lock them up if he can, and pretend the peoples eaſe: it is too much for them to go up thither, eſpecially ſince
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:170447:44"/>they have made <hi>Calves</hi> at their own homes: what need a Church when the highwayes of <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Bethel</hi> will ſerve the turne? Thus when he had cheated them into a civill war, they run madly to their own confuſion, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually weakning the powers of one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther till the forreign <hi>Aſſyrian</hi> enemy ſeized on both. Under which captivity, ten revolt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing tribes loſt both their names and beings: If in the mean time a <hi>Prophet</hi> come with a meſſage from the Lord to reduce theſe wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring ſheep, and bring them home to their forſaken folds, <hi>Jeroboam</hi> preſently ſtretches out his hand againſt him; and if a miraculous power from heaven do not whither it, that hand will lay him faſt. 'Tis reported of <hi>Julian</hi> that Enemy of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, that although he himſelf was an able Clerk, yet he hated and forbade all learning in others, left they ſhould detect his cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning fallacies: The compariſon I know is very odious, and yet I fear me we ſhall finde in our dayes more barbariſm: <hi>Meroz,</hi> curſing <hi>Tabor:</hi> When the people have broken off their golden earings for their <hi>calf, Aaron</hi> himſelf ſhall be threatned, if he will not dance about it. Nay further yet; fooliſh, ignorant, lying <hi>Zedekiah</hi> ſhall have leave to ſmite <hi>Micaiah</hi> on the face if he preſume to be ſo honeſt to diſwade his Countrimen from
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:170447:44"/>a warr, and prevail ſo far with thoſe that are in power as to clap him up in priſon: God quit <hi>England</hi> from <hi>Jeruſalems</hi> ſins of ſtoning thoſe which are ſent unto her.</p>
            <p>But fourthly, their curſes come not <hi>for not helping the Lord.</hi> Unleſſe they could perſwade us there are two <hi>Gods</hi> in Heaven, as they would make two <hi>faiths</hi> and more then two <hi>baptiſmes</hi> upon the Earth: For was ever the cauſe of God ſet up by <hi>lying?</hi> Lying, ſo palpable, ſo notorious that <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmines piae frauds</hi> were religious, if compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with it: every week being a <hi>Cretian Mart</hi> where the Devill ſends us in impreſſions by the whole ſale, which may teach the next Generation how voluminouſly wicked their Fathers were; Was ever Gods cauſe ſet up by <hi>oppreſſion?</hi> Cruel, inhuman, barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous oppreſſion, where one ſubject ſhall be armed with power to kill another. Whilſt the mouth of the <hi>Laws</hi> are ſtop'd and they outroad by <hi>Ordinances:</hi> Where every diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contented Country boor ſhall challenge an Equall ſhare in his Neighbours goods, and fall a plundering by the <hi>liberty of the Subject:</hi> Liberty! Licence let us rather call it, licence <hi>qua deteriores ſumus,</hi> an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe of licence which makes us worſe. Was ever Gods cauſe ſet up by <hi>Blaſphemy?</hi> Moſt execrable deep mouth'd blaſphemy,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:170447:45"/>which a ſober Chriſtian would be afraid to hear, leaſt the Divel ſhould be in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence: Some daring in the Pulpits (which I my ſelf have heard) tell Almighty God, that if he deſerted this cauſe he would looſe his honour, none would e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver call upon his name again. Others profeſſing in that ſacred place, if this cauſe failed they ſhould turne <hi>Atheiſts,</hi> as I think they are already: I will not tell all, you hear too much allready. Oh Sirs, we are cheated of our Religion: The mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſter Papiſts have rob'd us of ſome of the choyceſt of our Refined Doctrine whilſt we are degenerated into the dregs of <hi>Jeſuitiſme:</hi> Shall they make proffers of their ſervice to hazerd their lives and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes in the juſt defence of a good Prince, which notwithſtanding hates their Religion although he cheriſhes their ſubjection? and ſhall we unchriſtianly imagine that we <hi>help the Lord</hi> by deſtroying the <hi>Lords Anointed?</hi> The <hi>Giants</hi> may as well ſay they raiſed thoſe mountains for bulwarks to defend the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens from whence they meant to ſcale them: <hi>Judas</hi> may as well ſay he had given his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter a kiſs of courteſie when he brought out men with ſwords and ſtaves to ſecure him. Horrour and amazement keeps in the reſt.</p>
            <pb n="75" facs="tcp:170447:45"/>
            <p>Laſtly in their ſenſe (I ſay) God ha's needed <hi>no help againſt the mighty.</hi> For com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare <hi>Deborahs</hi> Eſtate to <hi>Siſeras,</hi> and make an equall reference in all to our own Nation and ſee who might properly be called the mighty: <hi>Deborah</hi> was under a palm tree in the high way, whilſt <hi>Siſera</hi> dwelt in <hi>Haro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth.</hi> You may all remember the time when his <hi>ſacred Majesty</hi> was firſt driven to theſe parts, when (except his goodneſs) there was nothing about him like a Prince, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you look upon his retinue, or his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion or the homage of his vicegerents as he paſſed: all ſo much inferior to his Eſtate, that had thoſe beheld it, which could have wiſht it meaner, I perſwade my ſelf, they would have pitied it: under the burden of which humility he muſt needs have faln, if his heart had not proved like <hi>Deborahs palm tree:</hi> grown higher with depreſſing. <hi>Siſera</hi> at this time abounding with all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion, <hi>Deborah</hi> ſeeks out for ſuccour to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter him: but thoſe as you heard come in very ſlowly and unarmed: her enemy had made a party in thoſe Tribes ſhe truſted to. When the neceſſity of a warr was made (which God knowes was moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>welcome news to the religious heart of our pious Soveraign) (witneſs thoſe ſeveral condeſcentions to almoſt unequal termes of
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:170447:46"/>peace, as would make a marble heart thaw to tears, that reads them) think but with what difficulty he raiſed up any forces, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member what oppoſition he found in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring a guard for his royal perſon, (indeed he needed none he had a guard of Angels,) that being quarreld at for him in an open Country, which his Courts of Juſtice thought neceſſary for themſelves in the greateſt place of ſecurity: I ſhould diſtruſt your judgments to remember you of <hi>Dans</hi> ſhips or <hi>Aſhers</hi> coaſt Towns, <hi>Reubens</hi> diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons or <hi>Gileads</hi> confaederacy: What ever the wit of man could invent, to ſtop ſupplies by ſea or land, of monyes, or men, or ammunition, what ever diſheartning could be thrown upon his well affected ſubjects; what ever oppoſition could be made by an <hi>aſſociation,</hi> entred between <hi>Geball</hi> and <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> and <hi>Ameleck</hi> the <hi>Phylistines,</hi> and thoſe that dwell at <hi>Tire,</hi> all theſe and more then theſe he incountred with: But <hi>non eſt conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium contra altiſſimum:</hi> In the day of battle <hi>Deborah</hi> wins the field: wonder not if the power of Heaven prevail Againſt the arme of fleſh: <hi>Though his excellency reach unto the Heavens and his head mount up to the clouds yet he ſhall periſh for ever like his own dung, Job.</hi> 20.6. Mount <hi>Tabor</hi> can tell you, and ſo can rebellious <hi>Meroz</hi> too, how ſuccesfull
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:170447:46"/>thoſe <hi>Northern</hi> troops have been, which God rais'd up as a pledg of his providence over his anointed, which all that look upon impartial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, muſt needs conclude with an <hi>hic Dei digi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus:</hi> This is the hand of Heaven which has de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended the <hi>Lord of the earth Againſt the mihgty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I haue cut out theſe ſo large a ſhare in my text that I have kept for our ſelves but a very ſmall diviſion: What ever remains two words ſhall diſpatch, 1. <hi>Imprecemur,</hi> 2. <hi>Deprecemur:</hi> let us curſe, and let us pray: Curſe thoſe that have deſerved it, pray that we may not deſerve it. <hi>Imprecemur</hi> firſt: Curſe if not with <hi>Deborah, Meroz</hi> there for <hi>not helping the Lord</hi> yet with St. <hi>Paul Meroz</hi> here for <hi>fighting againſt the Lord:</hi> In denoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing which ſentence I claſh not with the doctrine <hi>I</hi> have delivered. There is an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangelicall curſe for all ſuch coyned to my hands, and that the deepeſt of all other, no leſs then damnation. <hi>Whoſoever reſiſts ſhall receive to himſelf damnation Rom.</hi> 13. Had we the art of <hi>opening</hi> our bibles, and <hi>reading</hi> there, as well as <hi>wearing</hi> them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der our armes, which we love ſo well, we had been taught this divinity from as many plain texts as there are found to confirm any <hi>Article</hi> of the <hi>Creed:</hi> But a ſeeming devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is no new vizor. <hi>Horace</hi> tells us of the light wenches in his dayes, that <hi>Libellos ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>icos
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:170447:47"/>jacere inter ſericos pulvillos amant:</hi> they would not go to bed, but their grave trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſes of chaſtity muſt be their pillows: pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion I know is very good, but it is when the hearts and lips are friends: But if <hi>we walk not honestly toward them which are without,</hi> we teach <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Mahumetans</hi> to blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme our God, and whereas their religion is their ſhame, we prove a ſhame to our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligon. For conſider I beſeech you, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider ſeriouſly againſt whom ye would take up armes? Is it not againſt the <hi>power,</hi> againſt the <hi>ordinance</hi> of God? <hi>Contra animatam Dei Imaginem,</hi> againſt the walking picture of Heaven? In <hi>Kings,</hi> ſayes <hi>Lactantius,</hi> there is a double appearance: they are <hi>Men</hi> before <hi>God</hi> but they are <hi>Gods</hi> before <hi>Men:</hi> Such (ſayes <hi>Optatus</hi>) as acknowledg no power to controul them, but him alone which inſtated them in ſuch power: And who that is <hi>Tertullian</hi> will tell you elegantly: <hi>Inde Imperator, unde &amp; homo antequam Imperator, inde poteſtas illi &amp; ſpiritus:</hi> St. <hi>Pauls</hi> words ſhall interpret him, <hi>there is no power but what is ordained of God.</hi> Which ſtrook good St. <hi>Bernard</hi> to ſo brave are reſolution, that maugre the confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deracy of the world, he would prove himſelf a Chriſtian to God by a loyal ſubjection to his Soveraign: his words deſerve letters of Gold in his 170. Epiſtle. <hi>Si totus orbis</hi>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:170447:47"/>(ſayes he) <hi>adverſumme conjuraret, ut quip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piam molirer adverſus regiam Majeſtatem ego tamen Deum timerem, &amp; ordinatum adeo Regem offendere temere non auderem.</hi> And he gives his reaſon: <hi>Nec enim ignoro ubi legerim qui potestati reſistit, Dei ordinationi reſiſtit.</hi> See how vaſt a difference here is between our Spirits: Religious ſoul! the whole <hi>earth</hi> combining could not make him willingly offend his <hi>King:</hi> and ſhall the fear of a threatned <hi>plundering</hi> make us oppoſe our <hi>King?</hi> Alas Sirs, thoſe that we fear for the thorns to wound us, ſhould be the ſpurs to incite us: Do their worſt it is the beſt for us: they can but rob us of our <hi>intanglings,</hi> as <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ophilact</hi> gloſſes upon 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Some Serpents that imbrace us, and <hi>hinder us from pleaſing him who has called us to be Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers:</hi> ſhall we embrace a little nick named favour here, before the Eternal love of God? ſhall the common rout perſwade me to go to Hell for company? If the name of <hi>Chriſtian</hi> be not worn out with ſome newborn title for which we have exchanged it, think what our <hi>Captain</hi> hath done before us: He curſes <hi>Peters</hi> ſword, which was drawn in defence of him his Lord and Maſter, and when the judg of Heaven &amp; earth ſtood before the bar of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> to be adjudged, he confeſſes himſelf to the author of that power which ſpoke
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:170447:48"/>his own condemnation. 'Tis truely ſaid that Kings have long arms, they can reach to heaven for vengeance, they can crow'd down to hell for torments: And this is true of all Kings, Chriſtians, or Heathen good or bad: not only of the <hi>Veſpaſians</hi> the ſweet governours, but of <hi>Domitian</hi> the cruel Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, of <hi>Nero,</hi> of <hi>Tyberius,</hi> that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, (as his Maſter <hi>Gadareus</hi> called him) <hi>that heap of morter tempered with blood.</hi> The Oyl upon <hi>Sauls</hi> head ſaved his throat (ſayes <hi>Optatus.</hi>) He was a wicked King, it is true, and deſerved to dy, but <hi>David</hi> was a good man, and durſt not be his executioner, <hi>dum timuit olenm ſervavit inimicum;</hi> the oyl with which he was anointed, <hi>David</hi> well knew would never ſink, but in deſpight of violence would ſwim uppermoſt. 'Tis true that God ſometimes refines his Church in the furnace of perfection, neither then does he leave it naked and diſarme it. But what are the Churches weapons? St. <hi>Anſelm</hi> had his <hi>dolere potero, potero flere,</hi> his ſighs and groans againſt the <hi>Gottiſh Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers:</hi> St. <hi>Bernard</hi> fought to death againſt <hi>Lewes</hi> of <hi>France, non ſcutis &amp; gladiis, ſed precibus &amp; fletibus,</hi> prayers and tears were his ſword and buckler, <hi>Nazianzen</hi> overcame <hi>Julian</hi> but it was <hi>Chriſtianorum lachrymis ubertim effuſis,</hi> by ſoftning his
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:170447:48"/>Adamantine heart with ſalt drops from their eyes: Thence flowes the only ſea which can overthrow <hi>Pharoahs</hi> hoſt. But alas! this is not our caſe: We prepare other armes againſt a <hi>Prince</hi> of another temper: One, whom if the firſt <hi>Chriſtians</hi> had known they would have made him more then <hi>the delight of Men,</hi> they would receive him as an <hi>Angel</hi> of God. A Prince of ſo gratious a diſpoſition, that the grateſt fear his good ſubjects have to looſe him, is becauſe he is too good for Earth. One which lingers for <hi>peace</hi> in the greateſt ſucceſs of <hi>war:</hi> One which has hoped to <hi>win</hi> by <hi>looſing,</hi> and has willingly made himſelf leſs a <hi>King,</hi> if by that means he might make us more <hi>ſubjects:</hi> One which calls out for mercy in the field of blood: ye ſtones hear this and melt! for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidding the <hi>ſlaughter</hi> of thoſe which they can take <hi>priſoners,</hi> notwithſtanding they came out to be his <hi>executioners.</hi> Groaning for our wants, our infringed <hi>Liberties,</hi> our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cayed <hi>religion,</hi> which now lay expiring, but that the ſoul of it has found a warme ſeat in his royal breaſt. A true <hi>Cedar</hi> of Mount <hi>Lebanon</hi> that hath afforded a ſecure ſhelter to the humble vallies: and never, O never may he be cut down, till he be removed to the building of the Heavenly <hi>Sanctuary:</hi> As for thoſe trees that would have the <hi>bramble</hi>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:170447:49"/>raign, let them be conſumed by the bram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles <hi>curſe,</hi> and be burnt up with the <hi>fire</hi> which the bramble kindles. But I have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got my ſelf:</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Deprecemur,</hi> The great God of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven remove this curſe from us, for let us no longer flatter our ſelves, Brethren, with a ſuperficiall <hi>Allegiance:</hi> have we been as zealous for <hi>God</hi> and the <hi>King</hi> as our duty binds us? have our <hi>Eliahs</hi> cried as loud, have they rent and cut themſelves as much as <hi>Baals</hi> lying Prophets? Has not the fear of <hi>Daniels den,</hi> the place where the Kings <hi>Lions</hi> were kept, and <hi>Jeremiahs dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon</hi> ſtopped the mouths of our Men of God? Did not <hi>Deborah</hi> here find better aid from <hi>Zebulon,</hi> of thoſe <hi>that handle the writers pen?</hi> whereas, after the groaning of the preſs vvith ſeditious Pamphlets, our gracious <hi>Soveraign</hi> makes a juſt complaint that all pens are ſilent in his righteous cauſe: If he do <hi>gladio protegere,</hi> ſhall not we <hi>calamo defendere?</hi> If his ſword <hi>rights</hi> our cauſe, ſhall not our quils <hi>write</hi> his? He that fights for Heaven and us, ſhall not our prayers fight with Heaven and wraſtle with Almighty God for him? Shall a little of <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> his gold, ſend the <hi>ſqinzy</hi> in our throats? Shall a politick ſilence ſtop our Mouths? For, good Sirs, what ſhould you fear; the loſſe of your
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:170447:49"/>
               <hi>Eſtates?</hi> Alas, if you let fall this cauſe, who can challenge a propriety? 'Twill be in vain to preach a <hi>non concupiſces,</hi> thou ſhalt not wiſh, when a <hi>vote</hi> turnes you out of all <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rutis caeſis receptis?</hi> Do you fear the loſſe of Liberty? Was it ever more infringed? Do you fear the loſſe of <hi>Religion?</hi> I, here indeed it pinches: We have betrayed the cauſe <hi>Amyclaeo filentio,</hi> whilſt we durſt not tell you, the enemy was a coming: <hi>They have taken away the Lord, and we know not where they have laid him:</hi> Nay they have not left ſo much as the <hi>white cloaths</hi> in the place where he lay before: They have defaced the <hi>Sanctuary,</hi> and yet we the <hi>Nehemiahs,</hi> the <hi>Eliaſhibs,</hi> the Prieſts and Labourers, have taken neither a <hi>ſword</hi> in one hand to defend it, nor a <hi>trowell</hi> in the other to repair it. God be mercifull unto our ſin, for it is great, <hi>we have not holpen the Lord Againſt the might.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But the King ſhall rejoyce in thy Strength, O Lord; exceeding glad ſhall he be in thy Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Thou ſhalt give him his hearts deſire; and wilt not deny him the requeſt of his lips. For thou ſhalt prevent him with the bleſſings of good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; and ſhalt ſet a crown of pure gold upon his head. His honour ſhall be great in thy Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; glory and great worſhip ſhalt thou lay upon him. For thou ſhalt give him everlaſting felicity; and make him glad with the joy of thy
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:170447:50"/>countenance. And why, becauſe the King putteth his truſt in the Lord; and in the mercy of the moſt Higheſt he ſhall not miſcarry. All thine enemies ſhall feel thy hand; thy right hand ſhall find out them that hate thee. Thou ſhalt make them like a fiery oven in the time of thy wrath; the Lord ſhall deſtroy them in his diſpleaſure, and the fire ſhall conſume them. Their fruit ſhalt thou root out of the Earth, and their ſeed from among the Children of men. For they intended miſchief against thee, and imagined ſuch a device as they ſhall not be able to perform. Therefore ſhalt thou put them to flight; and the ſtrings of thy bow ſhalt thou make ready against the face of them. Be thou exalted Lord in thine own ſtrength, ſo will we ſing and praiſe thy power.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>Amen, Amen.</closer>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:170447:50"/>
            <head>The Third SERMON.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <pb facs="tcp:170447:51"/>
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:170447:51"/> 
                  <hi>NUMBERS 17.8.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>And it came to paſs that on the morrow <hi>Moſes</hi> went into the Tabernacle of Witneſs, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, the rod of <hi>Aaron</hi> for the houſe of <hi>Levi,</hi> was budded, and brought forth buds, and bloomed bloſſoms, and yielded Almonds.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THen it appears that time was when <hi>Aaron</hi> had a <hi>rod;</hi> and that <hi>rod budded</hi> too, yes and it <hi>budded</hi> in the <hi>Tabernacle,</hi> and was laid up in the <hi>Ark</hi> of the <hi>Covenant</hi> to be <hi>kept for a token againſt the Rebels in the latter dayes, verſe</hi> 10. And may not we fear that thoſe lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter dayes are faln upon us, when <hi>Aarons rod</hi> is now broken, and he himſelf ſcarce ſuffered to enter into the <hi>Tabernacle?</hi> Whilſt an <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> brood, ſit in the <hi>Temple</hi> of <hi>God</hi> which <hi>exalt themſelves above all that is called God.</hi> The Author to the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brews,</hi> chap. 9. tells us of three <hi>ſacra depoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta,</hi> holy Utenſils laid up in the <hi>Ark</hi> toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the <hi>pot</hi> of <hi>Manna,</hi> the <hi>Tables</hi> of the <hi>Covenant,</hi> and this <hi>budding rod:</hi> and there they kept company ſo long, that now they
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:170447:52"/>will not be parted. Let one be baniſht and all the reſt (we may fear) will follow: Once break the <hi>Croſier,</hi> this paſtorall <hi>rod,</hi> and the <hi>Tables</hi> of the <hi>Covenant,</hi> the <hi>ten Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendements</hi> are not long liv'd after it: They ſhall be baniſht out of the Church by ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legious deformers, &amp; out of the heart by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious <hi>Antinomians;</hi> and the <hi>pot</hi> of <hi>Manna,</hi> the heavenly bread of holy doctrine, ſhall be poyſoned with the <hi>Coloquintida</hi> of errors mixt amongſt it: there will be <hi>mors in olla,</hi> till ſome <hi>Eliſha</hi> poure in <hi>meal,</hi> better ground, better ſifted principles, there is death in the pot. <hi>Doctrine</hi> and <hi>Diſcipline</hi> like <hi>Hippocra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes</hi> twins will alwayes either laugh or cry to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.</p>
            <p>The words read may be called <hi>Gods lottery;</hi> the <hi>lots</hi> are <hi>rods,</hi> the <hi>bag</hi> they are put in is the <hi>Tabernacle,</hi> the hand that drew them out is the hand of <hi>Moſes,</hi> the <hi>houſe</hi> they fall on is the houſe of <hi>Levi.</hi> Or more plainly, it is Gods miraculous preferring the houſe of <hi>Levi</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> moſt eminently of all that Tribe; before the mutinying Congregation: They depend upon the foregoing Hiſtory, and I ſhould handle them very partially; if I did not preface them with it.</p>
            <p>When the <hi>Levite Cora<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> thought himſelf undervalued, that he was only ſeparated from the Congregation to do the <hi>ſervice</hi> of
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:170447:52"/>the <hi>Tabernacle</hi> and to <hi>Miniſter</hi> to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; eſteeming it but a ſmall thing that the Lord had thus <hi>brought him neer unto himſelf</hi> (indeed his ambitious heart, kept him at far diſtance) when the <hi>Priesthood</hi> was intayl'd on <hi>Aaron</hi> and his Succeſſors: he joynes himſelf to <hi>Dathan</hi> and <hi>Abiram, two ruling Elders</hi> of the Tribe of <hi>Reuben</hi> with two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and fifty Princes of the <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> and there begins to preach <hi>parity,</hi> a doctrine ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily diſgeſted by ambitious minds to this <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependent</hi> Congregation. A pretence of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe cloaked their wickedneſſe: For be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing gathered into a riot and daring do all acts of violence which their ſtrength could ſecure them in, they exclaim againſt their governours, <hi>you take too much upon you,</hi> ſay they, <hi>ſeeing all the Congregation are holy and the Lord is amongſt them: Wherefore then lift yee up your ſelves above the Congr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gation of the Lord?</hi> A ſtrange preſumption which the mad World will never leave, to entitle <hi>God</hi> to the <hi>Divels</hi> cauſe, to bring the Lord of Order to countenance their diſorders: but theſe unhappy dayes hath left the ſtory at our own doors; where a ſpecious outſide guilds many rotten Hypocrites: <hi>Sampſons</hi> two foxes cannot be coupled with a fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brand of Sedition between them, but they be reported abroad to draw the yoke of <hi>Jeſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:170447:53"/>Chriſt:</hi> under a pretence of <hi>Every one is holy,</hi> a <hi>parity</hi> in righteouſnes, every one ſtrives for a <hi>primacy,</hi> a <hi>ſupremacy</hi> in wickedneſs. And it were well if theſe thruſts were made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Aaron</hi> the <hi>high prieſts</hi> breaſt plate only, <hi>Moſes</hi> his <hi>rod</hi> is beaten down too. The <hi>Miter</hi> cannot fall but the <hi>Crown</hi> ſhakes; they that made <hi>Religion</hi> their qnarrel juſt before, preſently after make <hi>politicall grieveances</hi> the burden of the ſong. <hi>Moſes</hi> like a good Prince had taken off the envy from his High-Prieſt <hi>Aaron,</hi> and pointed their arrows at an higher mark: <hi>you are gathered against the Lord,</hi> ſayes he, (and indeed Sirs God is in all his ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances) <hi>but what is Aaron that yee murmur a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him?</hi> Yet let his next work be, to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure himſelf: <hi>Is it a ſmall thing</hi> (ſay they) <hi>that thou haſt brought us out of a Land that flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth with milk and honey to kill us in the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, except thou make thy ſelf a Prince altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther over us?</hi> This ſtrong complaint of <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny</hi> was the moſt forcible cord that could unite the hands of the many-headed-mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter-multitude. But the next verſe tells us it was their own particular intereſts which ingaged the Rebells, it was becauſe they had not <hi>Fields and Vineyards to their hearts deſire. Abſolom</hi> may flatter the people in the gate, and pitty their caſe that juſtice is delayed them, but let his heart comment upon his
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:170447:53"/>words, and he pitties moſt his own caſe, that he is not in place to do it. But <hi>Moſes</hi> can eaſily waſh his hands of Tyranny: <hi>I have not taken aſs from them, neither have I hurt one of them,</hi> ſayes he. The complaint of Rebels moſt commonly is as far removed from <hi>truth</hi> as their quarrell is from <hi>goodneſs:</hi> Yet un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs God from Heaven will atteſt his inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity, his own righteouſneſſe will ſcarce de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend him againſt two hundred and fifty <hi>aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly men. Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> fall upon their faces, but the Lord holds them up; and at their command the Congregation ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parates from the tents of <hi>Corah</hi> and his Confederates, who would have made them <hi>Separatists</hi> from the Congregation: Whilſt thoſe mutinying Traytors which did not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve to live, are not ſuffered to dye, but are buryed before their death, and they which would have made a diviſion from their <hi>Fathers</hi> may not be gathered to their Fathers in peace: <hi>But the earth opened her mouth and ſwallowed them up, they and all that appertained to them went down alive into the pit, and the earth cloſed upon them, and they periſhed from amongſt the Congregation.</hi> As for the other 250 with cenſers in their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nds which would be flaſhing of <hi>strange fire</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord, God ſends down a true <hi>fire from Heaven</hi> which eats them up: Two pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarell
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:170447:54"/>judgments: A <hi>Schiſme</hi> of the Earth puniſheth a <hi>Schiſm</hi> of the People; a <hi>fire from Heaven</hi> conſumes their <hi>ignis fatuus,</hi> their falſe <hi>fire</hi> upon the Earth; ſo ſurely does God overtake thoſe which do not carry him along with them in their deſigns.</p>
            <p>By this time we would think that an aw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful reverence of <hi>Moſes</hi> &amp; <hi>Aaron</hi> was wrought upon the hearts of the Congregation by the finger of heaven: but ſeditious minds are reſtleſſe: Like <hi>Siſyphus</hi> his ſtone, if it be faln to the bottom, it muſt be rold to the top of the hill again: The People fly from the gaping of the Earth, and are afraid of the fire from <hi>Heaven,</hi> but having digeſted their <hi>Panick</hi> fears, next morning (like men hardened to their deſtruction) they dare challenge God to renew his judgments, by charging his Magiſtrates with the blood of thoſe which periſhed in their own rebellion; as if <hi>Moſes</hi> his <hi>rod</hi> which before had devoured the <hi>Egyptian</hi> mock-Serpents, had now feaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon the <hi>Rulers</hi> of the <hi>aſſembly,</hi> and <hi>Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons blue,</hi> and <hi>purple,</hi> and <hi>ſcarlet,</hi> were now al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together <hi>dyed in blood; ye have killed</hi> (ſay they) <hi>the people of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But unleſs thoſe whom they accuſe for their Murtherers prove their deliverers they are all but dead men <hi>for there is wrath gone out against them: Aaron</hi> at <hi>Moſes</hi> his command
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:170447:54"/>runs into midſt of the Congregation, takes the <hi>cenſer,</hi> puts fire upon the <hi>cenſer,</hi> puts on <hi>incenſe,</hi> and ſtands between the living and the dead, and <hi>makes atonement for the People:</hi> The mercy of a good Governour reſembles <hi>God</hi> from whom he has his Commiſſion: he is ready to ſpare and protect them that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire his deſtruction: knowing that his Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour dyed for them which crucified him; yet leaſt the death of fourteen thouſand and ſeven hundred ſhould in the next Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on be worn out and forgoten, God will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuate this ſtory with a laſting miracle, and that the mouthes of murmerers may for ever be ſtop'd he makes choiſe of <hi>Aaron ſymbolical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: the twelve Princes of the twelve Tribes caſt in their twelve rods, as</hi> Moſes <hi>appointed, with their names wrote every man upon his rod: and on the morrow</hi> Moſes <hi>went into the Sanctuary of the Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and behold the rod of</hi> Aaron <hi>for the houſe of</hi> Levi <hi>budded and bloomed bloſſomes and brought forth Almonds.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In proſecuting theſe words, <hi>Aquinas</hi> his rule ſhall be our guide: <hi>In omni Scripturae narratione historica</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>profundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to tenenda eſt veritas hiſtoriae, &amp; de ſuper ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituales rationes ſunt fabricondae:</hi> in any hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal narrative part of <hi>Scripture,</hi> the firſt prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple which we muſt ground upon is the truth of the hiſtory, and that foundation
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:170447:55"/>once laid we make our myſtical, ſpirituall interpretations, a ſuper-ſtructure. Give me leave hear then to make <hi>Aaron</hi> another <hi>coat</hi> and to <hi>imbroyder</hi> over the <hi>fine linnen,</hi> the groundwork of the <hi>hiſtory,</hi> with the <hi>Blew,</hi> and <hi>Purple,</hi> and <hi>Scarlet,</hi> and <hi>Gold,</hi> the ſeveral colours of the <hi>myſtery.</hi> Obſerve we then in this miraculous Election of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, the <hi>ſubject</hi> on which the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle was wrought, which falls under our notice, 1. In the <hi>ſimple,</hi> it was a <hi>rod,</hi> 2. The <hi>compoſit</hi> it, was <hi>Aarons rod,</hi> 3. The <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compoſit,</hi> it was <hi>Aarons rod for the houſe of Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vi,</hi> Secondly, the <hi>miracle</hi> it ſelf, branched out in 3, decrees: This <hi>rod</hi> at <hi>Aaron</hi> for the houſe of Levi, 1. <hi>Brought foorth buds,</hi> 2. <hi>Bloomed boſome,</hi> 3. <hi>Yielded almonds:</hi> Thirdly the circumſtances of <hi>time</hi> and <hi>place,</hi> like two Servants to attend upon it. It was <hi>on the morrow, In the Sanctuary:</hi> Theſe are the <hi>ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges</hi> thorough which we ſhall <hi>drive</hi> in this hours diſcourſe, which will hardly affoord us time to <hi>bait</hi> in them, but only with a run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning eye to overlook them.</p>
            <p>The ſubject of this miracle firſt was a <hi>rod,</hi> and this was choſen of God before any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as the moſt proper the moſt ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant: Indeed if we look upon things with a ſuperficial eye, there was nothing belonging to the <hi>high Prieſt</hi> which did not promiſe
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:170447:55"/>more, and might not better prove <hi>Aarons</hi> preheminence. His very <hi>garments</hi> which <hi>God</hi> preſcribed <hi>Exod.</hi> 28. to be made <hi>glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> and <hi>beautifull</hi> like <hi>Joſephs</hi> imbroidered coat, might have taught his Brtheren that he was his <hi>Fathers darling:</hi> Or the <hi>Urim</hi> and the <hi>Thummim,</hi> and the <hi>ſtones</hi> of his <hi>breaſtplate</hi> which afterwards delivered thoſe <hi>divinations</hi> to the people, might have proved their own <hi>Oracles,</hi> and witneſſed their praeferment. Or the <hi>golden bels</hi> upon the verge of his garment might have challenged that honour which is promiſed to the <hi>bells of the Horſes, Zach.</hi> 14.20. to be ſuperſcribed, <hi>Holineſs to the Lord.</hi> But <hi>ratio divina in medulla eſt non in ſuperficie:</hi> It is not the glorious outſide which <hi>God</hi> regards: That Almighty power which chooſes the <hi>weak</hi> things of the World to confound the <hi>mighty,</hi> and ſayes unto the <hi>dead bones, live,</hi> takes here a ſapleſs ſere <hi>stick,</hi> without either <hi>root</hi> or <hi>branch</hi> for a <hi>Scepter</hi> at the exaltation of his <hi>anoynted;</hi> and that which before was the <hi>inſtrument</hi> of working many <hi>miracles</hi> is now become the <hi>ſubject</hi> matter upon which a <hi>miracle</hi> is wrought. And this was moſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite to <hi>Gods</hi> intent and purpoſe in four re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects: 1. as it is <hi>ſymbolum poteſtatis</hi> a <hi>rod</hi> to <hi>rule</hi> and <hi>govern</hi> them: 2. As it is <hi>ſymbolum correctio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis,</hi> a <hi>rod</hi> to <hi>correct</hi> and <hi>ſcourge</hi> them, 3. As it is <hi>ſymbolum inſtructionis</hi> a <hi>rod</hi> to <hi>guide</hi> and <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct</hi>
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:170447:56"/>them, 4. As it is <hi>ſymbolum ſustentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onis,</hi> a <hi>rod</hi> to <hi>ſupport</hi> and <hi>comfort</hi> them: <hi>Power, Correction, Inſtruction, Suſtentation,</hi> are the four pinacles of <hi>Aarons</hi> Tower, which make him lift up his head above his fellows.</p>
            <p n="1">1. As a Rod of power. For of old the Prieſthood was not fetterd nor <hi>Aarons</hi> hands bound behind him: If we look to his firſt election. <hi>Exod.</hi> 4.16. We ſhall finde he was made <hi>Lord Chancellour</hi> to <hi>Moſes</hi> amongſt the <hi>Iſraelites: He ſhall be thy ſpokeſman unto the people ſaith the Lord:</hi> Afterwards he and his ſons were oftentimes the <hi>Lords high Stewards,</hi> which executed judgment upon the offenders. And when <hi>Moſes</hi> was called up to Mount <hi>Sinai</hi> to talk with <hi>God, Aaron</hi> and <hi>Hur</hi> were made the <hi>Lords high Conſtables</hi> to govern the people in his abſence. <hi>I</hi> deny not but that there was a Subordination of <hi>Power:</hi> the <hi>Croſier</hi> gave place to the <hi>Scepter: Aarons rod</hi> ſubmitted to <hi>Moſes.</hi> For in the fore-quoted place. <hi>Exod.</hi> 4. Where the <hi>Prieſt</hi> was made the <hi>Princes mouth,</hi> the <hi>Prince</hi> was made the <hi>Prieſts God. He ſhall be as thy mouth and thou ſhall be to him as God.</hi> As for that <hi>high Prieſt</hi> now a dayes which proves himſelf the Man of ſin by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alting himſelf above all that is called <hi>God,</hi> he had need build upon a firmer foundation
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:170447:56"/>then the Sandy <hi>Clementines,</hi> or their falſe <hi>Gloſſes:</hi> otherwiſe their honour will fall into the duſt: Becauſe the viſion bids <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, ariſe, kill and eat,</hi> therefore the <hi>Pope may depoſe Princes:</hi> becauſe <hi>Malchus,</hi> which being interpreted a <hi>King,</hi> was ſervant to the <hi>High Prieſt,</hi> therefore <hi>Kings were the Popes ſervants.</hi> You may well queſtion whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther theſe arguments had their riſes from the <hi>Brains</hi> or the <hi>Gutts</hi> of the <hi>Friers.</hi> And truly we need not wonder to ſee thoſe <hi>Mountains</hi> are brought low and level'd, if we do but conſider that the pride of the <hi>Clergy</hi> hath been caution enough to <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>People</hi> to look about them: that that <hi>Croſier</hi> has not been uſed as a <hi>Pastoral staff</hi> to <hi>catch</hi> the <hi>Sheep</hi> but to <hi>hook</hi> away the <hi>Crown,</hi> and <hi>Aarons Rod</hi> is turned to a <hi>Scepter</hi> of iron, <hi>to cruſh the Kings of the Earth in pieces.</hi> Yet a lawful ſubordinate power they have dele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated from God himſelf: yes, and that in Temporals too, however the policie of our State of late hath thought it otherwiſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient. For to omit the ſtory of <hi>Judas Maccabeus,</hi> who in the time of the Captivity of their Kings governed the people; we ſhall find <hi>Phineas</hi> the Grand-ſon of <hi>Aaron</hi> in the next generation executing this Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, who as a <hi>Prieſt</hi> the ſon of <hi>Eleazar,</hi> and as a <hi>Prince</hi> of the Congregation did judgment
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:170447:57"/>upon <hi>Zimri</hi> and <hi>Cozbi,</hi> the <hi>idolatrous adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers;</hi> And it is worth your obſerving how the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> recording this ſtory, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 106. makes choice of a word of double ſignificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to imply his double capacity; the word is <hi>Palal,</hi> which ſignifies either to <hi>pray</hi> or to <hi>exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute judgment,</hi> verſe 30. <hi>Phineas ſtood up and prayed,</hi> or <hi>Phineas ſtood up &amp; executed judgment:</hi> denoting not only the <hi>connaturality</hi> of theſe two, that <hi>executing judgment</hi> is a kind of <hi>pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> or <hi>ſacrifice</hi> to God, but likewiſe their <hi>compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibility</hi> to the ſame ſubject, that <hi>executing judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> is as proper an office of the <hi>Prieſt</hi> as <hi>pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> it ſelf: And thus is <hi>Aarons a rod of power.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But 2. as of <hi>power</hi> ſo of <hi>correction</hi> too and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the firſt patroniſes the ſecond: his <hi>power</hi> enables him for <hi>correction.</hi> By <hi>correction,</hi> I mean not a corporal ſcourging or whipping of the people, as the <hi>diſciplining Friers</hi> uſe upon themſelves and others upon their <hi>pennance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayes; Arons rod</hi> had no whipcord at the end of it: but a more piercing laſh <hi>circa potiorem partem,</hi> ſuch <hi>arrows</hi> which <hi>David</hi> ſpeaks of <hi>which enter into the ſoul:</hi> It is a <hi>tradatur Satanae,</hi> a ſhutting them out of the Congregation, and a baniſhing them from the camp of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> To this purpoſe, <hi>Levit.</hi> 13. God gives the <hi>Prieſts marks</hi> &amp; <hi>tokens</hi> to <hi>diſcover</hi> the <hi>leprous party,</hi> &amp; to make a <hi>difference</hi> between the <hi>clean</hi> &amp; <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean,</hi> and thoſe <hi>marks</hi> once found out, it is not
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:170447:57"/>
               <hi>Nobility</hi> of <hi>blood</hi> or <hi>greatneſs</hi> of <hi>power</hi> can ſecure the <hi>Leper</hi> or keep him within the pale: The <hi>crown</hi> on <hi>Uzzias head</hi> cannot hide the Leproſie on his <hi>brow,</hi> but <hi>Azariah</hi> the <hi>Prieſt</hi> will caſt him out. 2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 26. Indeed if there be <hi>Livor in oculis Pontificis,</hi> malice in the <hi>Priests</hi> eye, which diſcolours all he looks upon, and makes the moſt clear object ſeem full of <hi>leprous ſpots,</hi> their caſting out proves but <hi>brutum fulmen,</hi> potguns which make a crack but cannot wound: As the blind man newly recovered to his ſight by our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour in the Goſpel, becauſe he ſaw more then the high Prieſt, was ejected: Indeed they threw him out of the <hi>Church</hi> that he might be neerer <hi>God.</hi> But when it is done, <hi>clave non errante,</hi> with an unerring judgment: pronounced on thoſe <hi>markes</hi> which God has ſet: <hi>he is polluted, he is unclean, let him dwell alone, without the camp ſhall his habitation be:</hi> and were it not to prevent the application which is to come anon, I ſhould tell you, that in <hi>Goſpel</hi> there is a <hi>retenta ſunt ſi retinueritis,</hi> whoſe ſins (the <hi>Leproſie</hi> of the <hi>Soul</hi>) the <hi>Prieſt</hi> ret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ains by excommunication, they are retain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the ſevereſt <hi>correction</hi> of all other.</p>
            <p>But 3. As a <hi>rod</hi> of <hi>power</hi> &amp; <hi>correction</hi> ſo is the <hi>Prieſts rod</hi> a <hi>rod</hi> of <hi>guidance</hi> &amp; <hi>inſtruction</hi> too: It is the <hi>guiding ſtatue,</hi> the <hi>Vibilia</hi> ſet up in the <hi>croſspaths</hi> of ſin to guide the people in the way
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:170447:58"/>of <hi>Gods</hi> Commandments: Hereupon the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet Malachi</hi> makes the <hi>Prieſts lips the Cabinet of knowledg,</hi> and ſends the People to ſeek the Law at his mouth, 2 <hi>Mal.</hi> 7. From thoſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duit-pipes flow thoſe ſtreams which <hi>make glad the City of God:</hi> You know the ſtopping of the pipes deprives the tankard bearers of water as much as if the fountain head were dried up. As good no <hi>law</hi> as none <hi>divulg'd:</hi> And this was the miſery of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> under King <hi>Aſa.</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 15.9. <hi>For a long ſeaſon they had been without the true God, and without a Prieſt to teach, and without the law:</hi> Obſerve the connexion, no <hi>Prieſt</hi> to teach the <hi>Law</hi> for a while, and preſently the <hi>law</hi> it ſelf is quite forgotten. And this made <hi>Aaron,</hi> have <hi>golden bells</hi> as well as <hi>Pomgra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nats,</hi> the ſoundneſs of the fruit of the one is nothing without the tinkling of the other: <hi>Moſes</hi> made two <hi>ſilver trumpets</hi> as well as two <hi>stone tables,</hi> that the <hi>law</hi> might be <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtred</hi> in the one and <hi>proclaimed</hi> with the other: God admits nothing <hi>dumbe,</hi> nothing <hi>barren</hi> in his ſervice. The very Cattle which draw the <hi>arke</hi> muſt be <hi>milch kine,</hi> ſuch as give down their milk; and they muſt have <hi>calfes ſhut up at home,</hi> that they may <hi>low</hi> after them as they go: And this befalls not under the <hi>law</hi> alone, but under the <hi>goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel</hi> too, whoſe very name <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> implies
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:170447:58"/>as much; A <hi>good meſſage</hi> it is, but no meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage before it be delivered; which im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prints upon every Miniſters heart, S. <hi>Pauls vae mihi</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.16. <hi>Wo is me if I preach not the goſpel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly as to <hi>govern, correct,</hi> and <hi>guide,</hi> ſo to <hi>ſupport</hi> the people too <hi>Aaron</hi> has his <hi>rod;</hi> and a heavy load is laid upon it, if we look to the firſt inſtitution: 28 <hi>Exo.</hi> 38. <hi>He is to bear the iniquity of the offerings of the People: Pliny</hi> tells us of a poyſoned fountain of <hi>Arabia,</hi> where the ſhepheards pay the price of the ſheep that drink and periſh. Let <hi>Ezechiel</hi> interpret this, Chap. 3.17, 18, 19, 20, 21 Verſes, the ſum of all is this, <hi>the blood of the wicked ſoul which dyes in his iniquity, if he be not forewarmed and admoniſhed God will require at the watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans hands.</hi> Nay not only the <hi>inquity</hi> of the Peoples offerings but the offerings them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves lye upon the <hi>Prieſts</hi> ſhoulders. <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.1. <hi>He is ordained for Men in things ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaining to God that he may offer both guifts and ſacrifiees for ſins.</hi> Have the People of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended? The <hi>Prieſt</hi> ſhall make an atone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for them before the Lord. Has <hi>Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melech</hi> a curſe upon his family? ſend to <hi>Abraham</hi> he is a <hi>Prophet</hi> he ſhall pray for him and reſtore him. Is <hi>Hezekiah</hi> diſcomfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by <hi>Rabſhaketh?</hi> ſend to <hi>Eſayah</hi> he is a
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:170447:59"/>Prophet, he ſhall lift up his prayer for the remnant that is left. Is any man ſick? Let him ſend for the <hi>Ministers,</hi> not the <hi>lay-Elders</hi> (as ſome falſely interpret Saint <hi>James</hi>) and let them pray over him, and their prayer ſhall work for the health of his body and Salvation of his ſoul: Thus is the <hi>Prieſt</hi> the <hi>ſtaff</hi> which the people lean on: and in theſe reſpects amongſt many other a <hi>rod</hi> was the moſt proper ſubject for the miracle.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It was <hi>Aarons rod, Aaron,</hi> who was <hi>ſummus Pontifex,</hi> a <hi>Mountain</hi> (as his name imports) which overtops the reſt. <hi>God</hi> which is the <hi>God</hi> of <hi>Order</hi> would in no age ever leave his <hi>Church</hi> to the miſchiefs of <hi>diſorder</hi> and <hi>confuſion.</hi> Which <hi>Order, God</hi> obſerved as ſoon as there was a <hi>Church,</hi> and a <hi>Church</hi> there was ſo ſoon as their was a <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation,</hi> and Men upon the Earth to make it. And firſt the moſt honourable, the <hi>firſt born</hi> of the families were vertually called to this dignity, to pray, inſtruct, and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice for the reſt: Neither can I hear o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit St. <hi>Auſtines</hi> obſervation, that at the Creation where God brought foorth all other Creatures in abundance, ſtoring all the Earth with many <hi>individuums</hi> and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars of the ſame <hi>Species,</hi> as many beaſts, many birds, and the like, he made but one Man, and deviſed all the reſt ſhould flow
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:170447:59"/>from his loynes, and ſo acknowledg him their chief and principle; and ſo from him a lineal deſcent ſhould be derived by <hi>primo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geniture,</hi> in whoſe hands ſhould reſt the government of all the reſt; ſo that <hi>Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chick</hi> Government is <hi>(tantum non)</hi> natural.</p>
            <p>But when <hi>God,</hi> as I may ſay, had imbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyed his <hi>Church</hi> and formed them into a <hi>camp,</hi> he then immediately from himſelf without any ſuffrage of the <hi>People</hi> elects his <hi>Governours,</hi> and dignifies them with the <hi>rods</hi> of their authority. <hi>Moſes</hi> in the <hi>tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poralls, Aaron</hi> in the <hi>ſpiritualls.</hi> From <hi>God</hi> I ſay, immediately they were choſen; not by <hi>themſelves,</hi> not by the <hi>People.</hi> Not from <hi>themſelves</hi> firſt, for what power had a poor hireling Shepheard, <hi>Reuels</hi> Son in law to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage a whole army? what policy, what inſinuations could he uſe which was <hi>ſlow of ſpeech, ſtammering of tongue?</hi> Unwilling to receive his <hi>commiſſion</hi> when twas given him; unwilling to execute it when he had it; fearing thoſe very <hi>miracles</hi> which ſhould confirm him, flying from his <hi>rod</hi> now made a <hi>ſerpent</hi> which ſhould incourage him. Or grant that ambitious minds do politick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly decline that, which they moſt greedily af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, what was there here that could in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flame their deſires? <hi>pugna eſt de paupere reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o,</hi> a bare <hi>Soveraignty</hi> over naked Men
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:170447:60"/>whom they muſt guide through a tedious Wilderneſs, and feed and furniſh with all neceſſaries in a forty years journey; and when they have <hi>Canaan</hi> their deſires in view, then be ſwept away and leave them. Unlikely that any men aſpired to be thus miſerable or choſe ſo burthenſome a do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion. And more unlikely the <hi>People</hi> choſe them to it, who were more likely to <hi>rebell</hi> againſt them then to <hi>obey</hi> them: And for all their pains paid them no other <hi>tribute</hi> but that of murmerings and revilings, inconſtant fickle men whoſe queazy <hi>ſtomacks</hi> ſometimes affect <hi>garlick</hi> &amp; <hi>onions</hi> before <hi>quailes</hi> &amp; <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na.</hi> The <hi>Levites</hi> which but lately drew their ſwords with them, now bandy themſelves againſt them; and theſe which at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the Chapter <hi>give praiſe</hi> for a late <hi>deliverance,</hi> before the end <hi>murmure</hi> for a new <hi>affliction.</hi> But <hi>commiſſions</hi> ſigned from Heaven are armour of proof againſt all the <hi>conſpiraces</hi> of the Earth. <hi>Moſes</hi> knew, <hi>I am that I am,</hi> alters not; and though the <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> of the <hi>Congregation</hi> take <hi>cenſers</hi> in their hands, they do but kindle a <hi>fire</hi> to their own deſtruction, the <hi>braſs</hi> of their <hi>cenſers</hi> ſhall make a laſting <hi>Monument</hi> of their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion: That ſo long as the <hi>altar</hi> has a being, Men may learn from thence, that <hi>no Man may take that honour to himſelf, but he that was
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:170447:60"/>called of God,</hi> as was <hi>Aaron:</hi> 5 <hi>Heb.</hi> 4. And ſure the love of God was ſuch that he would chooſe none but the beſt of <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> for his <hi>Church;</hi> Had all the <hi>Princes</hi> of the tribe of <hi>Levi</hi> had an equall ſhare, they by an <hi>Ariſtocraſy</hi> would have bred an <hi>emula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> had all the <hi>People</hi> injoyed a <hi>parity,</hi> their <hi>Democraſie</hi> would have brought in <hi>confuſion;</hi> but exalting <hi>Aaron</hi> in the <hi>high Prieſts</hi> chair, and diſpoſing of the reſt in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate offices under him, <hi>God</hi> maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſo bleſſed a <hi>Harmony</hi> in his <hi>Church,</hi> as that it was an imperfect ſhadow of that bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>Harmony</hi> in heaven.</p>
            <p>But 3. It was <hi>Aarons rod</hi> for the houſe of <hi>Levi</hi> upon whom the <hi>priesthood</hi> was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tailed. The <hi>Reubenites</hi> thought they had a fair plea for it, becauſe they were the <hi>firſt born</hi> of their Father <hi>Jacob:</hi> and the other tribes wiſhed well toward it, witneſs the <hi>rods</hi> which every tribe put into the <hi>lottery,</hi> in hopes it might be taken. But <hi>God</hi> which is conſtant to all his purpoſes <hi>had choſen Levi of all the Tribes of Iſrael, to be his Prieſt: as the Man of God</hi> teſtifies 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.28. <hi>To offer upon his altar and to burn incenſe before him.</hi> And it is well that this <hi>honour</hi> was once eſteemed ſo great, that all the tribes were ambitious of it. When the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phod</hi> and the imbroydered coat were eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:170447:61"/>glorious: The dregs of <hi>Jeroboams</hi> cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions have a greater influence upon our times, who made <hi>Prieſts</hi> of the loweſt of the people; and when God requires the moſt <hi>comely bodies</hi> and <hi>proportionable counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances</hi> for his ſervice; If any by nature be made ſo <hi>decrepit,</hi> that he be unfit for any other imployment <hi>he will come and crouch and ſay, put me into the Prieſts office, that I may eat a morſel of bread.</hi> Yet this Act of <hi>God</hi> which made the <hi>Priesthood Levi's im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriation,</hi> as it debars others from affecting of it, witneſs the deſtruction of the <hi>Reube<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites, Dathan, Abiram</hi> and their Confederates, or ſo much as intermedling with it, vvhich coſt poor <hi>Uzziah</hi> dear, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.7, Who going to uphold the <hi>arke,</hi> vvas ſmitten down, ſo neither does it priviledge the <hi>Levites</hi> themſelves to perform his <hi>ſervice</hi> after their ovvn fancy: If <hi>Aarons</hi> own ſons <hi>Nahab</hi> and <hi>Abihu</hi> ſhall preſume to offer up any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>fire</hi> then that which deſcended from Heaven upon Gods <hi>Altar,</hi> that <hi>fire</hi> which ſhould <hi>conſume</hi> their ſacrifices ſhall <hi>devour</hi> themſelves. The <hi>ſervice</hi> of the <hi>Sanctuary</hi> muſt be intire: It will admit of no <hi>Mecha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicks</hi> to <hi>officiate,</hi> nor yet muſt the <hi>fiery zeal</hi> of <hi>Clergymen</hi> themſelves coyne any new fangled formes of <hi>ſervices</hi> and <hi>worſhip</hi> which <hi>God</hi> has not preſcribed. Both are
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:170447:61"/>enemies to <hi>Aarons rod</hi> here; for as the one <hi>break</hi> it in pieces or <hi>ſteal it</hi> away, and clap their own in the room, ſo the other bow it to their humor and make it crooked after their own fancy.</p>
            <p>Hitherto we have beheld the <hi>rod</hi> wither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and dead: let us now conſider it in the <hi>miracle</hi> and ſee what <hi>fruit</hi> it bears, which is branched in 3. degrees, it <hi>budded,</hi> it <hi>bloſſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> it <hi>brought forth Almonds.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Every tribe in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> had provided his <hi>rod,</hi> and every <hi>rod</hi> was ſtrip'd alike, and had the name of the <hi>Prince</hi> of the tribe ingraven on it, <hi>Aarons rod</hi> had no more <hi>ſap</hi> in it, no more <hi>earth</hi> about it. Onely it had <hi>Aarons</hi> name upon it: Where God has made a ſecret choice, he will make an open difference. They go to the wrong end of the ladder which climb up into Gods breaſt firſt, and there trace out thoſe unſearchable points of his <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection,</hi> and from thence ground themſelves upon their impoſſibility of <hi>barrenneſſe</hi> and <hi>fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling off,</hi> and by conſequence, their neceſſity of <hi>budding</hi> and <hi>bloſſoming</hi> and <hi>bearing fruit.</hi> Would ſuch a courſe as this have comforted <hi>Aaron,</hi> or ſatisfied the other tribes? What difference between a <hi>Log</hi> and a <hi>Tree</hi> before it ſpring again? But then is <hi>ſalvation</hi> ſure when you work it out: Then faith is alive when it is manifeſted by its works: Then
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:170447:62"/>is <hi>Aaron</hi> declared to be Gods choſen when his <hi>rod quickens.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>quicken</hi> it muſt or elſe he cannot be the <hi>choſen of God.</hi> No ſurer token of the <hi>life</hi> of grace then <hi>fruitfulneſs.</hi> Barrenneſs was baniſhed at the firſt creation out of his gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of the World. <hi>Increaſe and multiply,</hi> ſays he, to all his creatures, and if any fall ſhort <hi>cut it down, why combreth it the ground:</hi> And he that is not marr'd by the Divel, is always thus <hi>increaſing:</hi> he is alwayes going forward either <hi>budding</hi> new or <hi>ripening</hi> his laſt bloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom'd fruit. It was a curſe laid upon avarice <hi>Eſaiah</hi> 5.10. <hi>that ten acres of Vines ſhould yeild but one bath, and the ſeed of an Homer ſhould yeild but an Ephah,</hi> but one part for ten: ſure that is an incumbrance not a crop; and thoſe <hi>Vines</hi> are fitter for winters <hi>fire</hi> then ſummers <hi>vintage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor yet will <hi>ſtanding ſtill</hi> in the ſame condition, ſerve the turne, (as they ſay an Oak will for an hundred years together.) Tis a true ſaying in Divinity, <hi>qui Deo non progreditur, regreditur,</hi> he that goes not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to God, goes backward to the Devill: It was no excuſe to the idle ſervant, that had hid his talent, although he had <hi>buried</hi> it up for fear of loſing 'ont, and put it in a nap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kin for fear of ruſting of it: It was taken from him, for his negligence, he had gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:170447:62"/>nothing to it. Yet who is there here pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, that cannot ſtrike upon his heart and ſay, Lord, I am in a worſe condition? He was <hi>idle,</hi> I am ſinfull. He hid his talent and brought it to light again, I have ſpent mine, and can ſhew no portion of it. He did not ripen his bloſſoms, <hi>I</hi> have made ſtrip and waſt of mine. My beauty <hi>I</hi> have abuſed to <hi>voluptuouſneſs,</hi> my wealth to <hi>luxury,</hi> my wit to <hi>knavery,</hi> my <hi>zeal</hi> to hypocryſy, my <hi>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural ingeny</hi> to maintain <hi>ſchiſm</hi> and <hi>hereſy. U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinam neſcirem literas,</hi> O that thou hadſt gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven me no talent, that having little <hi>I</hi> might had the leſſe required: The <hi>heat</hi> of thy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit has ſometimes <hi>quickened</hi> in me the <hi>buds</hi> of grace, but the <hi>coldneſſe</hi> of my devotion has <hi>nipp'd</hi> them: Or if the <hi>warmth,</hi> the <hi>ſunſhine</hi> of thy mercy or the <hi>fire</hi> of thy judgments has <hi>thaw'd</hi> my <hi>frozen</hi> heart and made it vigorous enough to bring forth <hi>bloſſoms,</hi> the <hi>Prince</hi> of this ayr has <hi>mildewed</hi> them: Or if the fruit has been ſet, it has either been <hi>blown down</hi> by the <hi>ſtorms</hi> of Affliction, or <hi>wormeaten</hi> in the <hi>ſunſhine</hi> my proſperity, and grown <hi>rotten</hi> at the Core. Thus have our <hi>rods</hi> which ſhould <hi>bud</hi> and <hi>bloſſom,</hi> and <hi>bring forth fruit,</hi> turned like the ſorcerers to Serpents and ſtung us to death.</p>
            <p>Obſerve yet farther, as <hi>Aarons rod</hi> had three degrees of fruitfulneſs, <hi>budding, bloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomming,</hi>
               <pb n="110" facs="tcp:170447:63"/>and <hi>bearing fruit,</hi> ſo thoſe three degrees met at one ſeaſon, <hi>ſpring, ſummer,</hi> ana <hi>harvest</hi> was joyn'd together; as the one fed his hopes ſo the other confirmed his aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance. A comfort it was to <hi>Aaron,</hi> no doubt, to ſee the <hi>budding</hi> of his <hi>rod,</hi> that there was <hi>life</hi> in it, that God had <hi>quickened</hi> it, and yet we know that a branch cut down, ſo long as the ſtock of ſap which is in it, will feed it, it will do ſo. But when it ſhall prove like <hi>Jeremies</hi> tree planted by the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. <hi>Jer.</hi> 17.8. <hi>Which ſpreads out her root by the river, and ſhall not feel when the heat cometh, but her leafe ſhall be green, and ſhe ſhall bring forth bloſſomes:</hi> This is delight as well as comfort. And yet <hi>Hoſea</hi> calls <hi>Iſrael vitem frondoſam</hi> a vine full of leaves, <hi>Hoſea.</hi> 10.1. Although within a few verſes it wither'd and was plucked up. But where the <hi>fruit</hi> is come to perfection, grown hard and ripe, and laſting, then may it well be <hi>laid up in the Sanctuary, to testifie for him in the latter day.</hi> And ſurely, beloved, <hi>Aarons rod</hi> in a myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call ſenſe continues fruitfull to this day. No <hi>Sermon</hi> which you hear, which is but a <hi>branch</hi> cut off from the <hi>tree</hi> of Gods word, ſhall return in vain, but if it be <hi>dead</hi> to ſome, and prove the ſavour of death, it will <hi>quicken</hi> in others, and prove the ſavour of life unto life everlaſting: Thus the very <hi>budding</hi> of this
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:170447:63"/>rod, the watchfull attention of you that hear us, puts us in ſome hopes that <hi>our labour is not in vain in the Lord.</hi> Or if after hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, you fall a diſcourſing of ſome point de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered, praiſe the Preacher, commend the fitneſes <hi>ſemen accipitis, verba redditis,</hi> (ſayes St, <hi>Auſtin</hi>) good ſeed you receive, good words you give back: <hi>laudes veſtrae folia ſunt, fructus quaeritur</hi> (as he goes on) good words are but <hi>leaves,</hi> or at the beſt but <hi>bloſſomes,</hi> it is <hi>fruit</hi> we preach for: and this St. <hi>Matthew,</hi> calls Chap. 3. ver. 8. <hi>fruit worthy of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance:</hi> reſtorative <hi>fruit,</hi> which may be anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tidote againſt the <hi>fruit</hi> of that other forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den <hi>tree,</hi> which poyſn'd us all. If this <hi>fruit</hi> appear, it will <hi>teſtifie for us in the latter day; Us,</hi> that we are of <hi>Gods</hi> ſending, called of <hi>God</hi> as was <hi>Aaron.</hi> You that you are of <hi>Gods</hi> plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and if by him planted you ſhall never be rooted up. <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.13. Thus whilſt ſome are <hi>budding,</hi> others in the <hi>bloſſome,</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers <hi>grown ripe, God</hi> may every day receive a <hi>fruitfull harveſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>One word more, behold theſe <hi>Almonds</hi> grow upon the <hi>rod</hi> ſtill and are not gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed off: and it is a good reaſon which a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend <hi>Prelate</hi> has given, why <hi>Aarons rod</hi> was treaſurd up and not <hi>Moſes,</hi> becauſe this carried the miracle ſtill in it ſelf, whereas the wonders of that other <hi>rod</hi> were paſt
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:170447:64"/>and gone. Thoſe are rotten <hi>fruits</hi> which fall off from the bough that bears them. The parable in 13 <hi>Mat.</hi> Tells us of <hi>ſeed ſprung up haſtily amongst the ſtones, but becauſe it had not depth of Earth it withered.</hi> There is I know a ſort of <hi>Goſpellers,</hi> whoſe hearts on a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain are all on fire but are ſoon quenched a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain. <hi>Jonahs gourd</hi> cannot outgrow them: but ſmitten by a <hi>worm</hi> they <hi>wither.</hi> Thoſe are <hi>Gods</hi> Champions which <hi>ſtand faſt in the faith,</hi> thoſe are his choſen that <hi>fall not away,</hi> whoſe <hi>buds</hi> grow <hi>bloſſomes,</hi> whoſe <hi>bloſſomes</hi> grow <hi>fruit,</hi> and ſo they grow on in grace, from one degree unto another, till they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come <hi>perfect</hi> in the Lord of all perfection <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 2. Circumſtances yet remain, and I ſhall handle them but as Circumſtances, the <hi>Time</hi> and <hi>Place, On the morrow; in the Sanctuary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. For the <hi>time,</hi> this change was wrought on a ſuddain, one night was <hi>ſpring, ſummer,</hi> and <hi>harveſt</hi> to the <hi>rod, on the morrow</hi> it bore fruit. We muſt not limit the eternal <hi>God,</hi> to time; <hi>miracles</hi> are his works, and his works are like himſelf <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in an inſtant. And as the <hi>high Prieſt</hi> under the <hi>law,</hi> ſo the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> and <hi>Biſhops</hi> in the <hi>Goſpel</hi> on a ſuddain were advanced: There was but an <hi>inſufflavit,</hi> he breathed upon them, and with his breath
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:170447:64"/>they received the <hi>holy Ghost.</hi> Which <hi>Spirit</hi> ſo changed their Spirits that it amazed their Adverſaries to behold ſuch <hi>Idiots,</hi> as Saint <hi>Luke</hi> calls them, Acts 4.13. men <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned</hi> and <hi>ſimple,</hi> command ſo many <hi>tongues,</hi> and cure ſuch <hi>diſeaſes:</hi> So what the <hi>Schools</hi> ſay of the <hi>Apostles,</hi> I may ſay of this <hi>Rod, probatur Deus per Virgam,</hi> as this ſuddain change proves <hi>Aaron</hi> and the <hi>Apostles</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment came from <hi>God,</hi> ſo by them it proves there is a <hi>God,</hi> ſince none but he could work the Miracles.</p>
            <p>Then <hi>ſecondly</hi> for the place, 'twas <hi>in the Sanctuary,</hi> and no place ſo fit as Gods own Houſe for Gods own Work. That houſe which <hi>budded</hi> in <hi>Davids</hi> thoughts, for which God commends him, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 3.18. But it <hi>flouriſhed</hi> in <hi>Solomons</hi> hands, who raiſed the glorious ſtructure of it: And however the zeal of ſome in theſe wretched dayes, go about <hi>to eat it up,</hi> as the zeal of that eat up <hi>Davids</hi> Heart, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 69.9. or rather <hi>Christ</hi> in <hi>David</hi> typified, 2 <hi>John</hi> 17. Yet Gods Houſe it ſhall remain ſtill, ſo long as there be Nations upon the Earth to inhabit any other: and that in a twofold reſpect. Firſt as God dwells in it, it is his <hi>Temple:</hi> ſecondly as his <hi>ſervices</hi> are performed in it, it is his <hi>Houſe of prayer. My houſe,</hi> (ſayes the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 56.7. repeated by our <hi>Saviour</hi> in
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:170447:65"/>three <hi>Evangeliſts</hi>) <hi>ſhall be called the Houſe of prayer to all Nations.</hi> And now let the brain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick <hi>Separatiſts</hi> brood what conceit they liſt, that <hi>Temples</hi> were but ceremonial, and <hi>Chriſts</hi> Paſſion put them out of date: either they muſt grant the fulneſs of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> before the deſcenſion of the <hi>holy Ghoſt,</hi> and that all <hi>Nations</hi> met at prayers at <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> (which is ridiculous enough) or that whilſt nations, acknowledg a <hi>God</hi> to be worſhip'd, he ſhall have a Houſe to be worſhip'd in.</p>
            <p>And truly Sirs we need not wonder that <hi>Harons rod</hi> in our dayes ſeems <hi>withered,</hi> ſince the <hi>Sanctuary</hi> in which it is kept is ſo neglect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. But alas! What ſpeak I of the <hi>croſier,</hi> when the <hi>crown</hi> it ſelf has found the ſame doom. When the traytor <hi>Jeroboam</hi> ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the ten tribes of <hi>Iſrael</hi> againſt their King he forbids them to go to the <hi>Temple</hi> at <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> and ſets up his <hi>high-way Religion</hi> to worſhip his <hi>calfs</hi> at <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Bethel.</hi> Nay he drives away the <hi>Prieſts</hi> of the <hi>Lord,</hi> the Sons of <hi>Aaron</hi> and <hi>Levi</hi> (with the <hi>Sanctuary</hi> away goes the <hi>budding rod:</hi> They are <hi>Relatives</hi> you ſee, pull down <hi>Church government</hi> and the <hi>Church</hi> will not ſtand long after it) 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 13.9. and made him <hi>Prieſts</hi> like the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of other countreys: <hi>Whoſover comes to fill his hand with a young bullock and ſeven rams, the ſame may be a Priest of them that are no
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:170447:65"/>Gods.</hi> But what ſpeak I of earthly Princes, when neglect of the <hi>Sanctuary</hi> uſhers in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion againſt the <hi>King</hi> of heaven, Hence we finde thoſe precepts ſo frequently con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joynd of <hi>Obſerving Gods Sabbaths</hi> and reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rencing <hi>his Sanctuary.</hi> Tis ſtrange that the one ſhould be Morall the other Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſay the Heathen. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 74.8. <hi>they will burne up all the Synagogues in the Land.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſay the Septuagint (chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one letter) they will forbid all his <hi>festi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vals.</hi> But the firſt part of the verſe reconciles both, <hi>Let us ſay they destroy them altogether:</hi> ſo that no <hi>Sanctuary,</hi> no <hi>budding rod;</hi> on <hi>budding rod,</hi> no <hi>Aaron;</hi> no <hi>Aaron,</hi> no <hi>worſhip</hi> of <hi>God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus we have diſpacht the hiſtory of the Text, with ſuch inferences touched upon by the way, as could not well be bauk'd: Now ſince <hi>whatſoever was written of Old was written for our instruction,</hi> it will not be amiſs to ſee how this <hi>rod</hi> of <hi>Aaron</hi> points down to us, and is <hi>laid up to teſtify against theſe latter dayes.</hi> And firſt I muſt not baulk the next <hi>high Prieſt,</hi> next in time, though firſt in honour, our Saviour <hi>Chriſt,</hi> who although he ſucceded not of <hi>Aarons</hi> order but of <hi>Melchizedecks,</hi> yet he is the <hi>Architype</hi> and ſubſtance which that other <hi>Prieſthood</hi> ſhadowed. The <hi>Author</hi> to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> his ſaved me the labour of making an Analogy between them. And
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:170447:66"/>I hope his Offices without diſpute will furniſh him with a <hi>rod:</hi> as a <hi>King,</hi> a <hi>rod</hi> of <hi>power</hi> and <hi>correction,</hi> as a <hi>Prophet</hi> of <hi>guidance</hi> and <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction,</hi> as a <hi>Prieſt,</hi> of <hi>comfort</hi> and <hi>ſustentation.</hi> In vain was that <hi>ſcape-goat</hi> of the <hi>Jewes</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whoſe head was laid the ſins of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, if it were not for this <hi>Lamb ſlain from the beginning,</hi> this <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, this <hi>high-Prieſt</hi> which ſacrificed himſelf, and laid, the burthen of all our ſins upon his own ſhoulders: He it is that took the <hi>cenſer</hi> in his hand as <hi>Aaron</hi> did, when the fire of Gods wrath was gone out againſt us, and <hi>ſtood between the living and the dead,</hi> nay he fell down amongſt the dead, and was <hi>num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred among the tranſgreſſours</hi> that <hi>by his ſtripes we might be healed.</hi> He, he it is who in the laſt act of his life erected his croſſe, the <hi>rod</hi> of his exaltation, that <hi>rod</hi> upon which <hi>his name was wrote,</hi> which bore moſt precious <hi>fruit,</hi> the <hi>fruit</hi> of his own Body, which whoſoever can <hi>lay up</hi> in a ſanctifyed heart, the <hi>Temple</hi> of the <hi>holy Ghost,</hi> may be ſure to have it <hi>teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fye for him in the latter day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But being thus <hi>gone up on high, and lead ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptivity captive, and received guifts for Men,</hi> is he grown a niggard of them, and beſtowed none upon his <hi>Church</hi> which he hath left be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind him? Were the <hi>Jews</hi> better provided for, who were only <hi>ad memoriam,</hi> but <hi>types</hi>
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:170447:66"/>and <hi>figures</hi> of him that was to come; then we which are <hi>a memoria</hi> his <hi>remembrancers,</hi> and <hi>Prieſts in his ſtead: in perſona ejus,</hi> ſayes the <hi>vulgar,</hi> his <hi>deputies</hi> which here perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate him and act him over again? No: his <hi>Church</hi> has <hi>Aarons</hi> ſtill, and the <hi>Aarons</hi> have their <hi>rods</hi> too: Nay the <hi>Aarons</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel</hi> ſhall be refined too ſayes <hi>Malachi</hi> 3. Chap. 3. <hi>God ſhall purge the Sons of Levi,</hi> which St. <hi>Hierome</hi> interprets the <hi>Evangeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Miniſters.</hi> If the <hi>Teſtament</hi> be above the <hi>law; God</hi> forbid the <hi>Miniſtration</hi> ſhould be beneath it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>St. Paul</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. tells us of divers <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> free graces or gifts proceeding from the <hi>Spirit</hi> verſe 4. and that we may not think them to be heaped confuſedly all upon one, in the next verſe he ſpeaks of ſeveral <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>adminiſtrations</hi> and <hi>offices</hi> among which they are devided, the <hi>graces</hi> are reckoned up verſes 8, 9, 10. Some peculiar to the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <hi>poſtles</hi> ſome ſtreaming down upon the skirts of the <hi>Church.</hi> The offices are recounted, v. 28. and of them likewiſe ſome meerly <hi>Apoſtolical,</hi> ſome permanent and perpetual; namely thoſe three, <hi>Teachers, Helpers, Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours.</hi> Perpetuall I call them, for beſides that the light of <hi>nature</hi> inſtructed the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, ſo far as the morality of the ſervice of a <hi>God</hi> carried them to the ſame diviſion
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:170447:67"/>of the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> their <hi>helpers,</hi> their <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> their <hi>teachers,</hi> and the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> their <hi>gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours,</hi> they are the very ſame which God preſcribed his own people the <hi>Jews,</hi> in their <hi>Levites,</hi> their <hi>Helpers,</hi> and as it were their <hi>Deacons;</hi> their <hi>Prieſts,</hi> their <hi>Teachers,</hi> and <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructers;</hi> the ſons of <hi>Aaron</hi> their <hi>Praelates</hi> and <hi>Governours.</hi> And thus we find the oynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentt powred upon <hi>Aarons, head has run down o his beard, and wet the borders of his garments.</hi> But this quick ſighted generation amongſt whom we live has ſeen farther into the words then any of the <hi>ancient Fathers,</hi> and out of the word <hi>Governours</hi> has extract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed an <hi>Elixar</hi> their ruling <hi>Elders.</hi> A Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment it is indeed, but ſuch as <hi>Jothams bramble</hi> was, which burnt down the <hi>Cedars</hi> of <hi>Libanon,</hi> the <hi>pillars</hi> of the <hi>Temple:</hi> An opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion ſo full of novelty and void of authority that fourſcore years ago it ſcarce had a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. As if <hi>Gods Church</hi> all the time before had been hid with <hi>Eliah</hi> in his <hi>cave;</hi> or <hi>fled with the woman into the Wilderneſſe.</hi> Some there are I know which have deeply ſtrained their wits to fetch this <hi>Government</hi> out of the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> and pinch hard upon that text, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.17. (when all other fail them) <hi>The Elders that rule well are worthy of double ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, eſpecially they which labour in the word, and Doctrine: Ergo</hi> by implication <hi>Elders</hi>
               <pb n="119" facs="tcp:170447:67"/>there are (ſay they) which labour not and thoſe are <hi>lay-ruling-Elders.</hi> But St. <hi>Chriſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome</hi> which lived nearer, and knew more of the <hi>Apostles</hi> practiſe than we, found out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother ſence. All <hi>Priests</hi> (ſayes he) which may <hi>adminiſter</hi> the Sacraments are not allow'd to <hi>preach:</hi> the meaner ſort may deal with <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> the wiſer only with the <hi>Word;</hi> Which difference St. <hi>Paul</hi> found in himſelf, 1 <hi>Corin.</hi> 1.17. <hi>Chriſt hath ſent me not to baptize</hi> (ſays he) <hi>but to preach the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel.</hi> If then thou haſt ſuch a <hi>Miniſter</hi> over thee as is gifted for <hi>both</hi> Offices, allow him a <hi>double honour.</hi> And let no man miſtake the name of <hi>Elder</hi> or <hi>Presbyter</hi> in Scripture, which is no other then <hi>Prieſt</hi> or <hi>Miniſter,</hi> ſo St. <hi>John</hi> ſtiles himſelf in his two laſt <hi>Epiſtles,</hi> ſo St. <hi>Peter</hi> 1 <hi>Ep.</hi> 5.1. and ſo all the pen men of Gods holy Word have called the <hi>Miniſters</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel.</hi> Which is ſo noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly true, that the very patrons of this <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment</hi> have diſclamed the <hi>jus divinum</hi> of it, and make it onely a State convenience: Undenyably true it is that our <hi>Saviour</hi> in his time did chooſe his twelve <hi>Apoſtles</hi> as <hi>Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours,</hi> his ſeventy as <hi>ſubordinate. Subordinato</hi> I ſay they were; for beſides that they were forbidden by the other in the time of Chriſt, <hi>Luke</hi> 9.49. They were commanded by them afterward as <hi>Silas</hi> was by <hi>Paul, Acts</hi> 17.15.
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:170447:68"/>and ſo were within their power. Afterward that the <hi>Apostles</hi> left their ſucceſſours <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops</hi> may be evident by St. <hi>Pauls</hi> own <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pistles,</hi> to <hi>Timothy</hi> the <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Epheſius,</hi> and <hi>Titus Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Crete,</hi> and the undoubted teſtimony of <hi>Ireneus</hi> confirms it, who lived immediately upon the <hi>Apostles</hi> age: But what need we more Authority? St. <hi>Jude</hi> v. 11. Speaks of ſome in his time <hi>which periſhed in the gainſaying of Corah.</hi> What that was, ye have heard; he would be <hi>Aarons</hi> equall, how any could periſh in it was impoſſible, unleſſe by deſiring or af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting a <hi>parity</hi> with their <hi>Governours.</hi> In the fear of <hi>God,</hi> Brethren, ſuffer then a word of Exhortation: This <hi>rod</hi> of <hi>Aaron</hi> ha's <hi>ſap</hi> in it ſtill and <hi>ſprouts</hi> to this day. Oh ſhake not of the <hi>bloſſomes,</hi> pluck not off the <hi>fruit:</hi> if <hi>God</hi> have laid it up in the <hi>Tabernacle,</hi> let not <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crilegious</hi> hands ſteal it thence: Tis a <hi>rod</hi> of <hi>power,</hi> ſubmit to it, a <hi>rod</hi> of <hi>correction,</hi> be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid of it, a <hi>rod</hi> of <hi>instruction,</hi> obediently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it a <hi>rod</hi> of ſuſtentation, rely on it. <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey them which are ſet over you in the Lord.</hi> Let no <hi>Uzzah</hi> preſume to touch the <hi>Ark;</hi> nor <hi>Uz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ziah</hi> to <hi>offer ſacrifice,</hi> let the ſons <hi>Levi</hi> only wait upon the <hi>altar.</hi> If a <hi>quis aequiſivit,</hi> be terrible at the laſt day, <hi>who has required theſe things at your hands?</hi> will not <hi>prohibita ſunt, have I not fobid thee;</hi> be much more terrible?
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:170447:68"/>We find in <hi>Exodus</hi> that <hi>Pharaohs</hi> ſorcerers had got them <hi>rods</hi> too, but <hi>Moſes</hi> his <hi>Serpent</hi> ſoon devour'd them: And the Sons of <hi>Sceva Act.</hi> 15.19. would be conjuring in the name of <hi>Jeſus;</hi> but the Devil ſoon prov'd himſelf their Maſter. Beware that fearfull curſe which befell the <hi>nolumus hunc regnare,</hi> thoſe that would not let <hi>Christ</hi> raign over them: And ſuch are they that deſpiſe his <hi>Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> and ſo do all ſuch as diſobey his <hi>ſubsti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes.</hi> His <hi>ſubſtitutes</hi> I call them, for they are his <hi>Labourers,</hi> but one degree remov'd from himſelf, he is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> they <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> he is, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> they <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: if God be the <hi>chief guide, Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> are the hands to lead his people: if <hi>God</hi> be chief <hi>Shepheard, Peter</hi> and his partners have the office under him <hi>to feed the flock.</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5. And if in <hi>temporalls</hi> the civil <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> at this day thinks himſelf ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent without bringing the <hi>difficulteſt cauſes to Aaron and the Priests,</hi> as <hi>God</hi> preſcribes <hi>Deuter.</hi> the 17.8, 9. if <hi>Jehoſhaphat,</hi> I ſay, think his Judges able to diſpatch <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>the affairs of State,</hi> yet let the <hi>Prieſt</hi> diſpence <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, 2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 19.8. <hi>The Lords buſineſs,</hi> the judgment cauſe of the <hi>Lord.</hi> Make not thy ſelf the Devils inſtrument, ſince he hath left <hi>diſputing</hi> about <hi>Moſes</hi> his <hi>body,</hi> for thee to diſpute <hi>Aarons authority.</hi> But rather joyn with that <hi>Captain</hi> of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in his prayer for
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:170447:69"/>
               <hi>Levi. Deuter.</hi> 33. <hi>Let thy Urim and Thumim be with thy holy one, bleſs O Lord his ſubſtance and accept the work of his hands, and ſmite through the loins of them that riſe up against him, and of them that hate him, that they riſe not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain.</hi> To conclude: <hi>Aarans rod</hi> is <hi>Gods rod</hi> and <hi>Gods rod</hi> will alwayes bring forth <hi>fruit,</hi> either ſweet or bitter <hi>Almonds:</hi> ſermons prove either the <hi>ſavour of Life</hi> or <hi>death.</hi> May that <hi>rod</hi> and this <hi>Sermon</hi> take ſuch deep <hi>rooting</hi> in our heart, that it may bring foorth <hi>fruit</hi> abundantly in our lives, to <hi>Gods</hi> honour his <hi>Churches</hi> glory, our own comfort, &amp;c.</p>
            <closer>Gloria Deo in Excelſis.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
